<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De causa Dei, or, A vindication of the common doctrine of Protestant divines concerning predetermination i.e., the interest of God as the first cause, in all the actions, as such, of all rational creatures, from the invidious consequences with which it is burdened by Mr. John Howe in a late letter and postscript of God's prescience / by T.D.</title>
            <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5533</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13687469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13687469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>De causa Dei, or, A vindication of the common doctrine of Protestant divines concerning predetermination i.e., the interest of God as the first cause, in all the actions, as such, of all rational creatures, from the invidious consequences with which it is burdened by Mr. John Howe in a late letter and postscript of God's prescience / by T.D.</title>
                  <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 123 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Roberts and are to be sold by Walter Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Thomas Danson.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 123.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Howe, John, 1630-1705. --  Reconcileableness of God's prescience of the sins of men.</term>
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DE CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SA DEI:</hi> OR, A VINDICATION Of the Common Doctrine of Proteſtant DIVINES, Concerning Predetermination: (<hi>i. e.</hi> The Intereſt of God as the firſt Cauſe, in all the Actions, as ſuch, of all Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures:)</p>
            <p>From the invidious Conſequences with which it is burdened by Mr. <hi>JOHN HOWE,</hi> In a late Letter and Poſtſcript, of <hi>GOD'S PRESCIENCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Roberts,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Walter Davis</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Mr. <hi>JOHN HOWE,</hi> Author of the late Letter and Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Preſcience.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I had read the Title-page of your late Letter to the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Mr. Boyle,</hi> and thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood its deſign, and withal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the ſmallneſs of the Bulk, I promiſed my ſelf that it would be <hi>Pagella, hoc ſolo nomine redarguenda, quod ſit tota Gemmea.</hi> For elſe I thought it would not be worthy of ſo great a <hi>Moecenas,</hi> a Maſter of all ſort of Learning; and <hi>[ſo]</hi> whoſe <hi>nobility is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Parchment,</hi> (as <hi>Charron</hi> ſpeaks): nor of the Author, (for I was aware of him, though he had concealed his name) whoſe parts I well knew (and have always had the candor upon all fit occaſions to acknowledge) were not of the lower ſize: nor yet of ſo excellent a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ſo needful in theſe dregs of time, which verge ſo much toward <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> And in the peruſal of the Letter it ſelf, for ſome time I pleaſed my ſelf with an apprehenſion that I had not impoſed upon my ſelf; nor had my affection to the Author ſeduced my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Fancy and Reaſon were in ſo happy a
<pb facs="tcp:101372:3"/>conjunction, that I hoped they would never be parted thoroughout the whole Diſcourſe. But alas! too ſoon I found my hopes ſhamefully baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled. For (beſide a corrupt gloſs upon <hi>Act. 4.28. pag. 28.</hi> which I could not digeſt, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers paſſages in the proceſs of your after-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe not unexceptionable) from <hi>pag. 32,</hi> to <hi>50,</hi> to ſpeak my ſenſe freely, I found <hi>pro theſauro carbones, i.e.</hi> Coals inſtead of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhining indeed, but black and ſmutty; politeneſs of ſtile, I mean, continued, but the ſeries of well-digeſted thoughts broken and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered; <hi>jejune</hi> Anſwers to Arguments full of ſenſe; old <hi>Popiſh</hi> Arguments dreſſed up <hi>A-la-mode,</hi> and many of which militate as much againſt your aſſertions as ours; and a great deal of good eloquence put to a very ill uſe, and a far worſe than it would be to play at <hi>Duck</hi> and <hi>Drake</hi> with broad pieces in the <hi>Thames;</hi> and ſometimes degenerate eloquence, which (like painted glaſs) though it was an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, yet impeded the tranſmiſſion of the light: and (which is worſt of all) the whole deſign of thoſe Pages I found to be an averment of the old <hi>Popiſh</hi> Calumny, that by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine God is made the Author of ſin; which I muſt needs profeſs was a ſtrange ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal to me; and ſo much the more, becauſe I could not conceive what ſhould induce you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proteſtant Divine, to make <hi>affidavit</hi> of a Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial accuſation, nor why in this Diſcourſe. For if the end you aſſigned your ſelf in doing
<pb facs="tcp:101372:3"/>it was the vindication of the bleſſed God from the imputation of being the <hi>cauſe of moral evil,</hi> you have certainly <hi>lurcht</hi> the Reader of his expectation, by offering nothing toward it but what he can eaſily ſee through, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that God is not the <hi>cauſe</hi> [univerſally] of <hi>natural good;</hi> or at leaſt as remote as the Grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of the Grand-child. [See your own words, <hi>Let. p. 36.</hi>] Two cauſes which might ſeem probable of your doing it in this Diſcourſe, your ſelf has removed out of your Readers way. It was not the requeſt of the Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom your Letter is directed, but (for ought I can collect) <hi>as the defending God's Predeterminative concourſe unto ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was an unenjoined task,</hi> Let. p. <hi>150.</hi> So was the overthrowing it too. Nor was it the connexion between Preſcience and Predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (as it lies in the Divine Decree, and is the only true ground of the certainty of Divine Preſcience) <hi>for that was not your deſign to demonſtrate Gods Preſcience of all whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever futurities, and conſequently of the ſins of men; but ſuppoſing it to ſhew its recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileableneſs with what it ſeemed not ſo well to agree,</hi> (as you ſince tell us) <hi>Poſtſc. p. 4.</hi> which I did eaſily apprehend before. For all the <hi>mediums</hi> you uſe for the eviction of this recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileableneſs, borrow no ſtrength from the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of <hi>Predetermination.</hi> Sometime after your Letter ſucceeded a Poſtſcript, in the view of which I was more aſtoniſhed than before: <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtupui
<pb facs="tcp:101372:4"/>ſteteruntque comae.</hi> For whereas I might have hoped that your ſecond thoughts would be better, they proved a great deal worſe. I had ſuch an opinion of your modeſty, that at leaſt you would recall the hard words you gave the Arguments urged for Predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſinful actions, <hi>Thin Sophiſtry, Colluſive ambiguity,</hi> Let. p. <hi>41. Vain at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, 38. Diſmal concluſions, 36. the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a Sophiſtical wit againſt ſenſe, and more againſt the ſenſe of our ſouls, and moſt of all againſt the entire ſum and ſubſtance of all Morality and Religion at once,</hi> p. <hi>39, 40. and overturning and mingling heaven and earth,</hi> p. <hi>50.</hi> And that reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you make upon thoſe <hi>who have uſed the diſtinction of</hi> voluntas ſigni &amp; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neplaciti, <hi>that they have only rather concealed a good meaning, than expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it a bad one,</hi> p. <hi>106.</hi> For take all together, and I ſee not that they amount to a leſs guilt, than of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rampling upon that venerable duſt, which was ſometimes anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by truly Heroick Souls, and bore the names of <hi>Zuinglius, Calvin, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za, Perkins, Pemble, Davenant, Twiſſe, Ames,</hi> &amp;c. than which no cauſe hath had, nor needs greater Patrons. But inſtead of recalling, you have avowed them, by the addition of others of the ſame ſort, <hi>a contagion, a deadly thing,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>15. An ill coloured opinion,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>51. Fearful conſequences of that rejected
<pb facs="tcp:101372:4"/>opinion; vanity of the ſubterfuges where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by its aſſertors think to hide the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it,</hi> p. <hi>50.</hi> Nor was this enough, but as if you were <hi>Animal gloriae,</hi> (as was ſaid of the Philoſophers) an animal that lived by the air of vain glory and applauſe, and thought your ſelf another <hi>Goliah,</hi> you cry out, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the armies of Iſrael this day; give me a man that we may fight together.</hi> What other interpretation are theſe words capable of? <hi>Now I perceive that ſome perſons, who had formerly entertained that ſtrange opinion of Gods Predeterminative concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the wickedeſt actions, and not purged their minds of it, have been offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with that Letter, for not expreſſing more reſpect unto it; and yet offered nothing themſelves (which to me ſeems ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſtrange) for the ſolving of that great difficulty and incumbrance, which it infers upon our Religion,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>7.</hi> Or theſe, <hi>If I find my ſelf obliged any way further to intermeddle in this matter, I reckon the time I have to ſpend in this world can never be ſpent to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than in diſcovering,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the inefficacy of the Arguments brought for it,</hi> p. <hi>50.</hi> but moſt immodeſt is your threatning thoſe that <hi>aſſert the contradictory to your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> with <hi>your preparations for the defence of it,</hi> and plain intimation of the value you put upon them, as ſufficient to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb facs="tcp:101372:5"/>all oppoſers, <hi>p. 51, 52.</hi> And for ought I can judg to the contrary, if contempt of your Antagoniſts will daſh them out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſo ſilence them, you are likely enough to obtain the victory you aſſure your ſelf beforehand. An inſtance whereof you have given us in your ill treatment of <hi>Mr. Gale,</hi> a moſt pious, modeſt, and learned man, and our common friend, and one who like a friend touched your ſore ſo gently, that one would have thought you ſhould hardly have cried Oh! much leſs have cried out of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive Hoſtility,</hi> p. <hi>16.</hi> and that he was the man that might be inſtanced in, that had <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged a publick conteſt with that candour and fairneſs, as not at all to intrench up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on friendſhip, which you did well know was poſſible</hi> to be done, (as you expreſs your ſelf, <hi>ibid.</hi>) And yet how many holes do you pick in his coat? one while you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate that he <hi>is of thoſe mens humours who take an unaccountable pleaſure, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praving what is done by others,</hi> p. <hi>12.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I who have known him about <hi>25</hi> years, and was of the ſame Academical Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety with you both, have never obſerved any ſuch misbehaviour of his. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other while, that he had <hi>a concealed end of his own glory,</hi> viz. [in attacking you], (as if the good man had coveted that inſcription upon his Tombſtone,—<hi>Magnis tamen excidit auſis).</hi> And again, aſſert
<pb facs="tcp:101372:5"/>that he <hi>had a mighty ſtrong and irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inclination to ſquabble a little with your Letter,</hi> p. <hi>13.</hi> And that <hi>this inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot but owe it ſelf to ſome peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar aſpect and reference he had to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> p. <hi>14.</hi> (whereas I dare be his vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that all the harm he wiſhes you is but an increaſe of humility). And this guilt you make account is faſtened upon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not attempted ſundry others of former and latter days, which have ſaid much to the purpoſe which your Letter does but touch on the by, <hi>p. 13.</hi> which is a ſtrange accuſation, and will appear ſuch to thoſe who ſhall upon peruſal find, that he hath run the hazard of his <hi>ſafety in medling with thoſe Giants</hi> you point at, <hi>Poſtſc. p. 14.</hi> But if he had not, I think he might apologize for himſelf, that your tract being conciſe, and adorned with good language, might invite more buyers and readers. Ratsbane capt in fine ſugar, may well be judged likely to entice ſome liquoriſh appetite to taſte of it, to their own hurt. But the greateſt provocation not to let you [whoever be let] paſs, is that intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reflection upon the Aſſerters of Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; upon their Arguments, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſequences of them, all at once in theſe words. <hi>But the effects of a Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal wit againſt ſenſe, and more againſt the ſenſe of our ſouls, and moſt of all againſt the entire ſum and ſubſtance of all Morality
<pb facs="tcp:101372:6"/>and Religion at once, are but like the attempt to batter a wall of braſs with ſtraws and feathers,</hi> Let. p. <hi>39, 40.</hi> This paſſage alone were enough to raiſe indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſufficient to make a diſputant (at leaſt if that paſſion be as effectual to that purpoſe as the old ſhred,—<hi>facit indignatio ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> intimates it is to make a Poet). And this was it that made me inquiſitive after an anſwer to your Letter, and Poſtſcript, as to which, when after many rumours of Anſwers preparing, I found my hopes fruſtrated, I reſolved (though almoſt too late) to attempt one my ſelf, for my reſolution was his in <hi>Terence, a quoquam alio quam a me, a me autem potius quam a nemine;</hi> that I had rather your anſwer ſhould come from any one than me, but from me rather than no body. I met with many diſcouragements in the laſt clauſe of my reſolution, in general from a conſciouſneſs of my own diſabilities, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly from the hard meaſure your other Antagoniſt <hi>Mr. Gale</hi> hath met with, as in the inſtances above-mentioned, ſo in ſome other. The one, your carping at words, that you make ſo ſevere Ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nadverſion upon him for an innocent Pleonaſm, The <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent will of God,</hi> which meant you no harm, nor was more <hi>guilty of any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> to rob your Eſſay of any part of its eloquence, than that was to <hi>pilfer from him any part of his collections,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>13.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:101372:6"/>And I was not without ſome apprehenſions that I might fall under your laſh my ſelf, who am not curious in the choice of words, or compoſure of periods. But againſt this fear I was ſomewhat relieved, as againſt the ſorrow I had conceived for <hi>Mr. Gales</hi> affront, (as if it had fell out for that end, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to juſtifie the old ſaw, <hi>aliquando bonus dormitat Homerus</hi>) by an happy accident that I have taken you tardy twice in that kind your ſelf: For what elſe but a Pleonaſm is that Phraſe, <hi>The rectitude of Gods holy nature,</hi> Let. p. <hi>42.</hi> and <hi>the rectitude of Gods own moſt holy will and way,</hi> p <hi>59.</hi> in the exceſs of your caution, leſt any ſhould think the holy nature, the moſt holy will and way of God were void of rectitude, <hi>Poſtſc. p. 22.</hi> And elſewhere <hi>actions malignantly wicked,</hi> p. <hi>32.</hi> i. e. <hi>wickedly wicked.</hi> But theſe are childiſh criminations, unfit to be bandied from hand to hand by ſober perſons. The other diſcouragement was the difficult in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation of your ſenſe, which I take to be a far harder task than to confute it; of which, that I may not be thought to complain without cauſe, I have collected ſome inſtances of repugnant and ſelf-contradicting Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in your Diſcourſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Mediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence.</head>
               <item n="1">
                  <hi>1. It ſufficiently ſalves the rights of the firſt cauſe, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert that no action can be done, but by a power derived from it, which in reference to forbidden actions, intelligent creatures may uſe or not uſe as they pleaſe,</hi> Let. p. <hi>36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> All actions good to <hi>Mr. Gales</hi> Queſt. <hi>Is there any action ſo ſinful that hath not ſome natural good as the ſubſtrate matter thereof?</hi> you Anſw. <hi>True,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Predetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion denied as to ſome actions, <hi>(viz.)</hi> evil.
<p>This is the deſign of all your Letter, from <hi>p. 32.</hi> to <hi>50.</hi> and of the Poſtſcript.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence.</head>
               <item n="1">
                  <hi>1. I do really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Gods immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate concourſe to all the actions of his creatures,</hi> Poſt. p. <hi>28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Some actions in themſelves evil.
<p>
                     <hi>Some actions of the creatures are in themſelves moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignantly wicked,</hi> Le. p. <hi>32.</hi> and <hi>intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally evil,</hi> p. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Predetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all actions granted.
<p>
                     <hi>The active provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God about all the actions of men conſiſts not meerly in giving them natural powers, whereby they can work of themſelves, but in a real influence upon thoſe powers,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>39.</hi> n. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>By which laſt clauſe, <hi>a real influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe powers,</hi> if you mean (as I cannot
<pb facs="tcp:101372:7"/>divine what elſe you can) a <hi>reducing thoſe powers into act,</hi> (as your phraſe is, <hi>Ib. n. 6.</hi>) you come over to our Camp, and we will give good entertainment to ſo ſerviceable a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter.</p>
            <list>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forces the will.
<p>
                     <hi>Nothing is more apparently a ſimple and moſt ſtrictly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural impoſſibility than not to do an action whereto the Agent is determined by an infinite power,</hi> Let. p. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Predetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion forces not the Will.
<p>
                     <hi>It is unreaſonable to imagine that God cannot in any caſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the will of a rational creature, in a way agreeable enough to its nature,</hi> Let. p. <hi>141.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Men are inabled by an internal infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of power and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal influence to do much good, to which they are not impelled by it,</hi> p. <hi>145.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>non eſt ingenii mei hoſce nodos diſſolvere,</hi> i.e. <hi>I have not wit enough to untie theſe knots.</hi> The conſideration of theſe repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, fills me with wonder at your exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>Mr. Gale,</hi> for finding no fault with your Pamphlet but what he makes, <hi>Poſtſc. p. 11.</hi> and particularly for ſuggeſting
<pb facs="tcp:101372:8"/>that <hi>your opinion falls in with the ſentiments of</hi> Durandus, <hi>which many think not well of,</hi> Poſtſc. p. <hi>9.</hi> For I muſt needs profeſs, that as far as I can judg, he hath but ſlandered you with a word of truth. For in your Letter, by which <hi>Mr. Gale</hi> did, and only could take his meaſures of your ſenſe, there's not the moſt implicite intimation of any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment, than to cloſe with <hi>Durandus.</hi> And though you do explicitely diſown it in your Poſtſc. yet you inſtruct not you Reader, how the Grammatical conſtruction of theſe words above cited, <hi>p. 36.</hi> of your <hi>Let.</hi> will yield any other meaning, than what <hi>Mr. Gale</hi> pitches upon. And the foreſight of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of being cried out upon for want of candour, in the ſame reſpects, did not a little deter me from the undertakement.</p>
            <p>A third, the neceſſity of making a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel between your and the Papiſts Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Predetermination, which I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw would give you occaſion to fault me, (as you do <hi>Mr. Gale),</hi> for parallelling your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions with theirs, the reaſon whereof muſt needs be becauſe I take a Papiſt for an ill-favoured name, <hi>Poſtſc. p. 27.</hi> yet here they are.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:8"/>
            <list>
               <item n="1">
                  <hi>1. Some actions are intrinſecally evil, and in themſelves wicked,</hi> Let. p. <hi>33, 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2. God hath as much influence and concurrence to the worſt actions, as the beſt,</hi> Poſt. p. <hi>25.</hi> [viz. <hi>by the Doctrine of Predetermination of ſinful actions.</hi>]</item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3. For God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine men to the worſt of actions, can mean no leſs thing than to impel them to do them,</hi> Let. p. <hi>37.</hi> which <hi>impelling</hi> you call <hi>an ineluctable fate,</hi> p. <hi>33.</hi> [and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>compelling.</hi>]</item>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4. God hath more influence and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the worſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions than the ſinner or tempter,</hi> Poſt. pag. <hi>25. and in more words,</hi> Let. pag. <hi>32. [viz.</hi> by our Doctrine.]</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item n="1">
                  <hi>1. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny actions ſo intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecally and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves evil, that they always are repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the eternal Law, and Right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Bell. de Am. c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Calvin <hi>was blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous againſt God in affirming, That God works evil works in us, ſo as he works good,</hi> Alvarez de Aux. Gr. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="3">
                  <hi>3. God, according to our Adverſaries opinion</hi> [viz. the Proteſtants] <hi>impells men, and ſo compells them to ſin,</hi> Bell. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="4">
                  <hi>4. God according to the opinion of</hi> Calvin <hi>and</hi> Beza <hi>is the primary Author of all ſins.</hi> Bell. c. <hi>4.</hi> de Amiſſ. Gr.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:101372:9"/>
            <p>But paſs upon this parallel what judgment you pleaſe, I am at a point. I have propoſed to my ſelf a good end in the exhibition of it, <hi>viz.</hi> to mind my Readers that the point under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between you and me is a ſtated controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between the Papiſts and Proteſtants, and therefore the affirmative not lightly to be rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from; and in drawing it up I gave my ſelf a little pleaſure mixed with diſdain; <hi>that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was no Smith found through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the land of Iſrael, you were ſain to go down to the Philiſtines to ſharpen your axe and your mattock, 1</hi> Sam. <hi>13.19, 20.</hi> And I admired that you could not excogitate one new Argument, but preſent us with all old, and ſtrangely unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, which have been bafled as often as urged. I have i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>titled my Anſwer <hi>De Cauſa Dei,</hi> rather than <hi>De cauſa Deo;</hi> which latter might be proper enough for the ſubject, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Gods intereſt as the firſt cauſe in all the actions of his Creatures. But herein I have imitated <hi>Bradwardine's Piety,</hi> who would ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thereby that it was the Cauſe of God he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſecure from the impetuous aſſaults of its Adverſaries, among whom I am heartily ſorry you ſhould be numbred, as to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. I know you will not own the charge, but pretend that you are on Gods ſide, but if ſo, you have neglected an opportunity of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelf, by <hi>not reconciling Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive methods of ſin</hi> with immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:101372:9"/>which is at leaſt as hard as with <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinative concourſe:</hi> and to be ſure, <hi>any one may ſee it was very idle and ludicrous trifling, to offer at reconciling thoſe methods with God's Preſcience, and to wave that (manifeſtly) greater difficulty of reconciling</hi> them with his immediate concourſe, <hi>if you think there is ſuch a thing,</hi> (to uſe your own words with but the variation that a diſſerent inſtance requires) <hi>Poſtſc. pag. 3, 4.</hi> I have been as brief as I could in my Anſwer, without prejudice to our cauſe; and have come (as <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> ſaid of the <hi>French</hi> in their Expedition into <hi>Italy</hi>) rather with Chalk in my hands to mark out the Inns, than with Arms to break through and take poſſeſſion. It will be time enough to arm when <hi>your Preparations ſhall riſe out of that duſt and ſilence in which they are buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Poſt. <hi>p. 51.</hi> In the mean time I have but pointed out the <hi>Fontes ſolutionum,</hi> the general grounds upon which our Anſwers depend, to all Arguments that can be produced. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I could heartily wiſh you would ſerionſly reflect upon your Letter and Poſtſcript, and conſider how many paſſages you are obliged to repent of and retract. Shall I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind you of that notable ſaying of <hi>Auſtin, Illius ſcripta ſumma authoritate digniſſima,</hi> &amp;c. i.e. <hi>his writings deſerve to be of the greateſt authority, who hath let ſlip never a word, not that he would, but that he ought to recall. He that hath
<pb facs="tcp:101372:10"/>not attained ſo much wiſdom as to be able to ſay nothing not to be repented of, may yet attain ſo much modeſty as to repent of what he knows he has ſaid amiſs,</hi> Aug. Ep. <hi>17.</hi> And for your encouragement, it may not be unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to mind you, of what you cannot but know, that <hi>Auſtin</hi> who gave this good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, did take it himſelf, and left upon record re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractation of his Errors, wherein he was a ſingular inſtance of humility, and was rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God with a greater eſteem in the Church than any one man ſince his time. Which is all, beſides that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 31. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your true Friend and Brother <hi>T. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101372:10"/>
            <div n="1-63" type="pages">
               <head>De Cauſa Dei.</head>
               <p>IT has been always judged very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Polemicks to ſtate the Queſtion, and explain the terms, when they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under any ambiguity, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever fall not under the apprehenſion of thoſe who are to be inſtructed, for want of skill in that art or ſcience to which they belong, or language from which they are borrowed. In neither of theſe reſpects will it be needleſs in the Controverſie now to be agitated; not as to the firſt, becauſe Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> gives us his ſenſe in various terms, and ſuch as ſeem repugnant to each other: one while that which he denies is, a <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminative concurrence</hi> to all actions of the Creatures, <hi>Let. p.</hi> 32. and <hi>Poſtſc. p.</hi> 3. and <hi>Predeterminative concourſe,</hi> Poſt. p. 19. another while 'tis <hi>Predetermining Influence,</hi> Poſt. p. 19. and a <hi>Determinative influence,</hi> Let. p. 36. and <hi>Efficacious influence,</hi> Poſt. p. 52. As for the two former phraſes (which are of the ſame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) they are in effect <hi>contradictio in adjecto</hi> in their conjunction. I appeal to <hi>Strangius,</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi>'s friend, but my Adverſary in the main Queſtion under conſideration, <hi>Hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101372:11"/>Predeterminationem nonnulli confundunt cum concurſu Dei generali quem concurſum praevium appellant,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i.e.</hi> Some confound this kind of <hi>Predetermination</hi> with the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral concourſe</hi> of God. But they ſpeak very improperly who call <hi>Predetermination</hi> a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious</hi> [or <hi>Predeterminative] concourſe,</hi> or ſay that God does by concourſe determine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes: and he quotes <hi>Twiſſe</hi> with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, ſaying, <hi>Concurrere cum agente aliquo modo,</hi> &amp;c. i.e. <hi>To concur with an agent ſome way to the production of an effect, is not to determine that agent. For the Creature alſo concurs with God to the production of an effect, and yet it does not determine God: therefore nor does God concurring with the Creature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it to act.</hi> Strang. de Vol. Dei, Lib. 2. Cap. 4. p. 161. <hi>Strangius</hi> does not call the terms a <hi>contradiction,</hi> I confeſs, but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon out of <hi>Twiſſe</hi> gave him as juſt ground (as it does me) ſo to call them. As for the latter phraſe, <hi>influence,</hi> which he makes equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent with the former <hi>concourſe,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>I here affect not the curioſity to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh theſe two terms as ſome do,</hi> Poſt. p. 29. <hi>I</hi> had rather he ſhould hear <hi>Strangius</hi> again, than me blaming his not affecting that curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity of diſtinction: <hi>Caeterum nobis operae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretium videtur diſtinguere inter iſta duo voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula concurſum &amp; influxum,</hi> &amp;c. i.e. <hi>But it ſeems worth our labour to diſtinguiſh between
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101372:11"/>thoſe two words</hi> Concourſe <hi>and</hi> Influence, <hi>which in this matter are often conjoined and confounded. For firſt, Influence is of a larger extent than Concourſe. For the cauſality of every Cauſe, especially the Efficient, is called Influence. And therefore in many inſtances there may be obſerved an Influence of God, when yet there is no concourſe, as when he acts, not making uſe of any ſecond cauſe. Again, although in the concourſe of two Cauſes each of them are conſidered as having their Influence, yet the word Influence is abſolute, and noting a reſpect to another cauſe; but the word Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is relative to another cauſe.</hi> Strang. de Vol. Deil. 1. c. 11. p. 59. As for the term <hi>Efficacious,</hi> it ſuits us well enough, if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> intends by it an Infallibility of the event, or the certain production of thoſe actions which God hath an Influence upon. The ambiguity of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> phraſes removed, and the ſenſe of them brought to a certainty, I aſſert the contradictory to his Propoſition, <hi>That God doth not by an Efficacious influence univerſally move and determine men to all their actions, even thoſe that are moſt wicked,</hi> Poſt. p. 52. Which if we might be allowed the liberty of our own terms, we would thus lay down, That God does determine, or prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, or move all Creatures to all and each of their actions. <hi>Strangius</hi> fairly enough cites our Theſis, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 155. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101372:12"/>then to be diſcuſſed is, Whether God does determine or predetermine all Creatures to all and each of their actions? So <hi>Strang.</hi> fairly, <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 155. Unleſs it may ſeem meet to add that <hi>reduplicative particle, as ſuch,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s addition, <hi>even thoſe that are moſt wicked,</hi> Poſt. p. 52. As to which it is to be noted, that we who aſſert Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of all actions of the Creatures, do limit it to the actions conſidered abſtractly from the moral good or evil adhering to them: as for inſtance, we hold Gods Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the natural act whereby <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> begat a child in Adultery, as well as of thoſe whereby he begat children in lawful Matrimony; and of the uſe of his tongue in telling a lie to <hi>Abimelech</hi> the Prieſt, as well as in praiſing God. Whereas Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Gods <hi>Predetermination only to morally [or ſpiritually] good actions as ſuch,</hi> Poſtſ. p. 39. n. 6. Which <hi>Predeter nation ſpecial,</hi> we grant; but withal aſſert <hi>a general,</hi> which extends to evil actions. In which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The ſubject;</hi> and as to this we ſay that ſin is in that which is good, the nature of man and his faculties and actions, and theſe God excites and guides efficaciouſly. And this <hi>ſubject</hi> is called the <hi>materiale</hi> or ſubſtrate matter of ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The end;</hi> and thus though not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101372:12"/>yet the exiſtence of ſin is good, or it is good that ſin ſhould be, becauſe God draws good out of it; and hence God predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines to the natural actions, though he knows ſin will adhere to them. The grand term then to be explained is <hi>Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or (as ſome Divines and Metaphyſicians ſometimes call it) <hi>Praecurſe</hi> and <hi>Praemotion,</hi> of which terms the former which ſignifies a <hi>fore appointment,</hi> is either from eternity, or in time. The latter two, only in time. The former <hi>(viz.)</hi> Predetermination, is either from <hi>eternity,</hi> and ſo is an immanent act of Gods, that is, of his will to produce in time all the actions of his Creatures; or in <hi>time,</hi> which is the actual production of all thoſe actions which he had decreed to produce. And of this latter only is the Queſtion to be diſcuſſed underſtood; and this act of Gods is called <hi>Predetermination,</hi> becauſe it limits the creature to this action rather than to that; and 'tis called a <hi>Precourſe,</hi> or <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion,</hi> i.e. a <hi>running before,</hi> or <hi>fore motion,</hi> (as I may ſo ſpeak), becauſe in order of nature it is before the action of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Again, <hi>Predetermination</hi> [or <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> or <hi>Premotion],</hi> is diſtinguiſhed into <hi>Phyſical</hi> or <hi>Moral.</hi> The latter, I grant may be aſcribed to God with reference to good actions as ſuch, but not with reſpect to evil actions, unleſs the propoſing objects
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101372:13"/>and occaſions of ſin may (as ſome learned men judg) be reduced to the actions of a moral cauſe. But whether the moral acts of God in commanding, threatning, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, &amp;c. may be juſtly denominated Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination, will remain dubitable till another doubt be reſolved, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Whether the will do always follow the laſt practical dictate of the underſtanding. Againſt the affirmative of which Queſtion (to note that <hi>obiter</hi>) the moſt acute and learned <hi>Wallis</hi> ſeems to oppoſe an irrefragable Argument, <hi>viz. that the Will then is not diſabled by the fall more than the will of the confirmed Angels and Saints in Heaven.</hi> Wallis <hi>Truth tried againſt the Lord</hi> Brook, <hi>p.</hi> 55. But let <hi>Predetermination Moral</hi> fall or ſtand, our Queſtion is not of that, but of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Predetermination,</hi> as appears in that we make it common to all creatures, ſome whereof are not capable of a <hi>Moral Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination,</hi> (ſuppoſing that to be) which yet is not intended to be agitated at preſent, but only that which is exerciſed about free agents, that is, rational creatures. Which that it may be done with more clearneſs, and may in part obviate ſome of our learned Antagoniſt's objections, we ſhall endeavour, with as much accuracy as is needful to a diſcourſe that will fall into other than learned mens hands, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101372:13"/>conſider <hi>Predetermination</hi> as contradiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, or oppoſed rather to two things, which are acknowledged by him as Gods Acts reſpecting the actions of free agents, (not excluding natural), <hi>(viz.) Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>immediate Concourſe,</hi> or <hi>Concurrence;</hi> the conceſſion of the former of which two, will not be ſound ſufficient to entitle God to the honour of the firſt cauſe of his creatures actions; and of the latter will (unleſs we take our meaſures amiſs) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force him to grant that <hi>Predetermination</hi> which now he denies. Firſt as to <hi>Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> we muſt obſerve, that as Creation ſtands oppoſed to nothing; ſo Conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Annihilation, <hi>i. e.</hi> making that ceaſe to be ſomething which was ſo; and it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from Creation only in this, that it notes a continuation of that being, and its powers and faculties, which were given by creation, as being a continuation of that action by which it was produced; and therefore is commonly ſtiled <hi>continua creatio,</hi> and not unfitly termed by the School-men <hi>manutenentia Dei,</hi> i. e. <hi>Gods hand-hold,</hi> becauſe by it God holds up all things, as it were, with an hand from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into nothing; by the withdrawing of which, Divines generally think the world would be annihilated.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As to <hi>concourſe</hi> or <hi>concurrence,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101372:14"/>it may be thus defined; <hi>It is an extrinſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of God, by which he does with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes, [or the creatures] immediately produce all their natural actions and effects.</hi> 1. <hi>It is an action of God</hi> to diſtinguiſh it from the power communicated and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſecond cauſes, (by which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their ſeveral operations) by <hi>creation</hi> and <hi>conſervation.</hi> 2. <hi>Extrinſick</hi> to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it from his Decree of this action cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>concourſe,</hi> which decree is an intrinſick action. 3. <hi>With ſecond cauſes,</hi> or the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe it is ſuch an action as joins with the creature; as when the Writing-Maſter and the Scholar ſhape the ſame letter by the Maſters guiding the Scholars hand. 4. I add, <hi>all their actions,</hi> and what is produced by action or the <hi>effects,</hi> as when the Maſter and Scholar write, not only is the action the ſame, but the effect; the letters are the ſame which are done by both together. 5. <hi>Natural actions and effects,</hi> to exclude what by accident ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to the actions and effects; which ſeeing they are defects, cannot be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by a proper efficiency, and ſo nor God concur to the production of them by ſuch efficiency. 6. <hi>Immediately produce,</hi> to note the intimacy of the conjunction of God with the creature in the production of natural actions; which is ſuch, that one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101372:14"/>and the ſame action is the action of God and of the creature.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to <hi>Predetermination,</hi> it is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined. <hi>It is a tranſient action of God which excites every creature to act.</hi> It is called <hi>a tranſient action of God,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Immanent,</hi> or the Will and Decree of God that the creature ſhould act. That is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from Concourſe or Concurrence thus. 1. The very difference of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, <hi>Prae</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> i. e. <hi>Before</hi> and <hi>with,</hi> notes that the former is in order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (though not of time), <hi>before</hi> the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures action, the latter with it. 2. That the former notes the reduction of the creatures powers into act: the latter notes Gods acting with the creature. 3. The former is to be conceived of <hi>per modum principii,</hi> under the notion of a principle, or cauſe of the creatures acting: the latter only, <hi>per modum actionis,</hi> i. e. as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Gods acting with the creature. 4. The <hi>Terminus</hi> or object of that action of Gods, which we call <hi>Predetermination,</hi> is the ſecond cauſe it ſelf, the reaſonable creature: but the <hi>Terminus</hi> or object of that action of Gods, called <hi>concourſe</hi> or <hi>concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> is the action of the ſecond cauſe, and effect produced by that action. So that the Queſtion in plain words is, <hi>Whether God does move men to all their natural actions,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101372:15"/>and ſo to one rather than another.</hi> The Proteſtants generally maintain the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and how forcibly Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it, remains now to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>The terms explained, we ſhall endeavour a defence of our Arguments, which Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> hath thought meet to ſingle out.</p>
               <p>The firſt of the two Arguments of ours; which <hi>ſeeming most importunate and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> he hath attempted to enervate, is.</p>
               <p>Arg. 1. <hi>That it neceſſarily belongs to the Original and Fountain-Being to be the firſt Cauſc of whatſoever Being; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that what there is of poſitive Being in any the moſt wicked action, muſt principally owe it ſelf to the determinative productive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of this firſt and Soveraign Cauſe: Otherwiſe, it would ſeem that there were ſome Being that were neither</hi> primum, <hi>nor</hi> a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, <hi>[i. e. neither the firſt Being, nor from the firſt Being],</hi> Let. p. 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which he Anſwers, <hi>It may well be thought ſufficiently to ſalve the rights and priviledges of the firſt Cauſe, to aſſert that no action can be done, but by a power derived from it; which in reference to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden actions, intelligent Creatures may uſe or not uſe as they pleaſe, without over-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting, that they muſt be irreſiſtibly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined alſo, even to the worſt of actions done by them,</hi> Let. p. 36.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101372:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> For the better underſtanding of our Argument, and the proof thereto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed; together with Mr <hi>Howes</hi> Anſwer thereunto, it will not be unneedful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to Syllogiſms: the Argument thus,</p>
               <p>All poſitive Being are effects of the firſt Cauſe. All ſinful actions, as actions, [for that is our limitation], are poſitive Beings. <hi>Ergo,</hi> All ſinful actions [as actions] are effects of the firſt Cauſe, [<hi>viz.</hi> God].</p>
               <p>The Major [or firſt propoſition] is proved by an Hypothetical Syllogiſm, thus: If all poſitive Beings are not effects of the firſt Cauſe, then there is ſome poſitive Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which is neither <hi>primum [ens]</hi> nor <hi>a primo,</hi> [i. e.] neither the firſt Being, nor from the firſt Being, [or which is neither God nor a Creature]. But there is no poſitive Being which is neither the firſt Being, nor from the firſt Being. <hi>Ergo,</hi> All poſitive Beings are effects of the firſt Cauſe. To the Argument it ſelf Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> replies nothing, nor yet to the proof, in form (as by the Laws of Argumentation he was obliged). But ſeems to diſtinguiſh in the Major between a double dependance, which poſitive Beings have upon God as the firſt Cauſe; one, that they have no power but from God; the other, that the exerciſe or uſe of that power is from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101372:16"/>God. The former he grants; the latter he denies, but with a limitation as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden actions.</p>
               <p>To which we Reply,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this Anſwer is fatal to his own Conceſſion of <hi>Gods immediate concurrence to all the actions of his Creatures,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 28. For it amounts to as much, as if <hi>in terminis,</hi> he had aſſerted a mediate concurrence only to ſome actions, (<hi>viz.</hi> forbidden actions; and this was the paſſage I preſume that gave Mr. <hi>Gale</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to charge Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> with <hi>Durandus</hi> his Opinion, which was, That God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs remotely and mediately with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cauſes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> no otherwiſe than as he confers and conſerves their Eſſence and Power of action, by which they themſelves act nextly and immediately. And for ought I can yet underſtand a very juſt occaſion; for though Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> in the place above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited acknowledges immediate concurrence; yet in the Letter it ſelf, by which Mr. <hi>Gale</hi> was to make an eſtimate of his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there was <hi>ne gru quidem,</hi> not a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is hard to conceive the reaſon of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s limitation; why forbidden actions ſhould be only by power derived from God; and good actions or indifferent, require alſo an irreſiſtible determination;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101372:16"/>when the material of the actions morally diverſified is often the very ſame. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, In the motion of my hand to kill another out of ſpleen and private revenge, or to kill my enemy in a lawful ſelf-defence, or to ſtrike my friend in merriment. I am aware that he attempts to wipe off the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion of ſymbolizing with <hi>Durandus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he denies immediate concourſe uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, whereas himſelf denies only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminative concourſe to wicked actions, <hi>Poſtſc. p.</hi> 28, 29. And be it ſo, that his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt hath been ſucceſsful, yet I muſt give <hi>Durandus</hi> the precedence of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> for ſagacity in this point; and do judg that he ſpake more conſonantly to himſelf, and the truth, when he affirmed that the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the power given to the creature, was ſo univerſal, as to extend equally to evil actions and to good. For it ſeems evident enough that all natural actions, as ſuch, [the Subjects of moral good and evil] muſt either have, or want immediate concurrence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Anſwer runs counter to Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s aſſertion elſewhere, <hi>That in reference to ſinful actions by this influence</hi> [determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native] <hi>God doth not only ſuſtain men who do them, and continue to them their natural faculties and powers whereby they are done,</hi> [which is all Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> hath granted us
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101372:17"/>hitherto in his Anſwer to our Argument, from the dependance of the ſecond Cauſe upon the firſt]; <hi>but alſo as the firſt mover, ſo far excite and actuate thoſe powers, as that they are apt and habile for any conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous action,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Poſtſc. p.</hi> 41. For if by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing and actuating the powers, he means that God reduces them to act, he hath taken a large jump from <hi>Durandus</hi> to <hi>Twiſſe:</hi> for the latter (nor we who follow him) neither ſays nor means any more by Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And we cannot tell what other meaning to affix to his words, without upbraiding him with ſtrange inadvertency in his choice of them. For elſe he conſounds Concurrence either with <hi>Conſervation;</hi> which latter keeps the powers apt and habile [as they are made] or with <hi>Predetermination,</hi> whereas this goes before, that goes along with the Creatures act.</p>
               <p>But now I attend to the proof of his ſtrange Aſſertion, for a proof I underſtand it to be) though he introduces it with a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides;</hi> (a particle which commonly is a ſign of an additional Argument) which thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Anſ. <hi>It ſeems infinitely to detract from the perfection of the ever bleſſed God, to affirm he was not able to make a creature of ſuch a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as being continually ſuſtained by him, and ſupplied with power every moment ſuitable to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101372:17"/>its nature, ſhould be capable of acting, unleſs whatſoever he thus enables, he determine [th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is, for it can mean no leſs thing, impel] it to do it alſo.</hi> Let. p. 36, 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. If we ſhould take liberty of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things by their appearance at firſt ſight, without giving our ſelves the trouble of a ſtrict diſquiſition, we might eaſily be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into an imagination, that it does no leſs infinitely detract from the Divine Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to affirm. That God was not able to make a Creature of ſuch a nature, as that it might continually ſuſtain it ſelf, without a ſupply of power every moment from God; for that opinion ſeems to tye God to a ſhorter tedder, than an ingenuous Artificer, who can raiſe an Edifice that ſhall laſt many years, without any need of his help for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations.</p>
               <p>And this I the rather take notice of, becauſe I find it the ſentiment of the moſt acute <hi>Suarez, That they who deny Gods immediate Operation in every action of the Creature,</hi> [which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſeems to do in his Anſwer now under diſcuſſion] <hi>will doubtleſs be compelled to deny that the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture does depend immediately upon the actual influence of God. For</hi> (which is his reaſon) <hi>that which depends not upon God in acting, nor does it depend upon him in its being.</hi> Met. Diſp. 20.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101372:18"/>
               <p n="2">2. This confirmation of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is guilty of two unpardonable faults in a man of Learning and Ingenuity, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a too early <hi>anticipation,</hi> and immodeſt <hi>begging</hi> of the main <hi>Queſtion.</hi> An <hi>anticipation,</hi> in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the <hi>impelling,</hi> i. e. <hi>compelling</hi> (for that is his ſenſe of the term, as will appear e're long) men to act, as the import of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determining; whereas there is no neceſſity of hooking in ſuch an import of it: for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it no way to abridg the liberty of the Will, yet by Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Argumentation, it is <hi>eo nomine</hi> to be rejected, becauſe the ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Creature and ſupplying it with power every moment ſuitable to its nature, [that is, in <hi>Durandus</hi> ſtile, <hi>mediate concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>] is to be judged ſufficient to enable the Creature to act, without determining it to action; upon no leſs peril to them that ſhall dare to judg it inſufficient, than to be reputed detracters from the Perfection of the ever-bleſſed God. And a <hi>begging of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> 'tis, which I may well call immodeſt, becauſe he knows we neither can nor will grant it, without ruining our Hypotheſis; nor need we do it, becauſe he elſewhere owns it <hi>unreaſonable to imagine that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any caſe determine the will of a rational Creature, in a way agreeable enough to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Let. p. 141.</p>
               <p>I confeſs he gives us here but an inch, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101372:18"/>we will venture to take an ell; I mean, to extend his conceſſion of ſome caſes to every caſe, and particularly to our caſe of ſinful actions. For let our ſentiment be burdened with what other load Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhall pleaſe (as the truth is he is not over merciful to the Predeterminants) I think he hath diſcharged it of forcing the will, till he hath evinced a ſpecialty in our caſe, which will be ſomewhat an uneaſie task, though we ſhould grant him his own option, that God predetermines to ſinful actions <hi>in concreto,</hi> i.e. to the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſinfulneſs of them too; for upon that ſuppoſition there is leſs neceſſity to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God cannot determine the will in a way agreeable enough to mans [corrupt] nature; becauſe he does but determine it to what it hath an innate propenſion to of it ſelf; and ſo Gods determination is but as the wind in a mans back, which puts him on a little faſter in the way he was going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are at a great loſs as to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s meaning, whether it be that it is a detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Gods perfection, to affirm, God was not able to make a Creature that could not act univerſally without determination, or particularly as to forbidden actions; the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the terms calls for the former ſenſe, the concluſion he was to prove, for the latter.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101372:19"/>
               <p n="1">1. If the former ſenſe be that he will own, I ſeem to my ſelf fairly allowed to infer, that then man in his primitive ſtate had not, nor have the good. Angels at preſent, any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine determination to good actions, becauſe to both unneceſſary; and unneceſſary it muſt be preſumed, becauſe it is a detraction from Gods Perfection to conceive he could not make them of ſuch a nature, as that they ſhould not need it, and becauſe they had no <hi>diſinclination to be overcome by an efficaciouſly determinative influence,</hi> (which is the reaſon Mr. <hi>H.</hi> gives of the neceſſity of Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to holy actions in the lapſed ſtate. <hi>Poſt. p.</hi> 35. Which if it be of any force makes it unneceſſary to a ſtate of Integrity.) And if this inference be natural, I wonder not that Man fell, but that he fell not as ſoon as he was ſet upon his legs; nor that ſome of the good Angels turned Rebels ſo ſoon to their Soveraign Lord, but how the reſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in their Loyalty. I have hitherto ſwom with the ſtream of Proteſtant Divines, (not becauſe it was eaſie, but in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion ſafe) who have conceived the good Angels ſecurity an effect of a greater degree of <hi>determinative influence,</hi> (to borrow Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Phraſe) or <hi>corroborating grace,</hi> that is, in the terms of the Queſtion now agitated, Predetermination, than was afforded to the [now] bad Angels; or to ſpeak more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101372:19"/>of the continuance of that Predetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the one, which was ſuſpended as to the other: which conception of Divines (to note that in paſſage) may be eaſily freed from the imputation of reflecting either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods Holineſs, Juſtice, or Truth; upon the firſt, becauſe God by the ſuſpenſion of Predetermination was no more the Efficient of the Angels ſin, than the Sun of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that overſpreads the air, when it hath withdrawn its rays; upon the ſecond, for it is a ruled caſe in the Schools, <hi>Non datur ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia proprie dicta inter Deum &amp; Creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras;</hi> i. e. <hi>God cannot be properly ſaid to be a debtor to his Creatures;</hi> no not when he hath paſſed a promiſe to them, for even then, (if we will ſpeak ſtrictly) he is a debtor to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, namely to his own truth and fidelity, not to them; and if he ſhould (to ſuppoſe an impoſſibility for illuſtration-ſake) break his word, he would be but <hi>Mendax, non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurius,</hi> a <hi>Lyar, not unjuſt.</hi> Not upon his Truth, for he was not under the bond of a promiſe, (as he is to the part of repaired Mankind, whom we denominate Saints) to preſerve the Angels from Apoſtacy. As for thoſe who take this Doctrine for a blemiſh upon Gods goodneſs, I turn them over to God himſelf, for a reconciliation of theſe two ſeemingly contradictory Propoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in his Word, and within the verge of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101372:20"/>our own experience, that God is good, and [yet] that he hath permitted a paſſage for ſin, which he could have impeded.—If the latter ſenſe be avowed, as a genuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s mind; I know not how it will be able to ſave its credit, if I ſhould charge it with being guilty of this groſs abſurdity, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſuppoſal that God made Man with an ability to do ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>in concreto,</hi> i. e. the natural actions, and ſin that adheres to them. 'Tis true, God made Man mutable, and how could he do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? (unleſs he ſhould have made him a God) which very terms involve an inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable contradiction) and ſo in a remote ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of ſinning. But Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a next or immediate capacity of acting, which the Creature is capable of, as ſoon as it ſtarts out of nothing into ſomething, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervenient aid of Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I am very averſe from thinking this to be Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s meaning; and I would offer him a friendly hand (if he would accept of it) to help him out of the pit he is fallen into, by minding him of our diſtinction between the <hi>materiale</hi> and <hi>formale</hi> of ſin, the natural acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is the ſubject, and the ſin that is the [inſeparable] adjunct, in our temporary eſtate: which diſtinction ſuppoſed, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nction with Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Hypotheſis, Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s meaning will be freed from the <hi>encumbrance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101372:20"/>now inferred upon it;</hi> and it will amount to no more than that the power of acting God gave to man, ſuffices to the natural actions, ſince ſin adhered to them, as well as before, without the help of Predetermination. But then this friendly hand will prove unfriendly in the iſſue; for though it may clear him of one, yet it will entangle him in many abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, or (at leaſt ſelf-contradictions: For then,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How ſhall he quit himſelf from the blame of being a Favourer of <hi>Durandus Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis?</hi> for the ſenſe is the ſame, and the words not much different. And yet why ſhould he once attempt it, ſeeing that Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis ſerves his profeſſed deſign of quitting God of the blame of being the Author of Sin, with much officiouſneſs: and that he may accept this ſuggeſtion the more kindly, a moſt Learned hand ſhall tender it to him: <hi>Some are of opinion that God hath no immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate influence, but mediate only, in reſpect of voluntary agents. And according to this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is eaſie to clear God from the imputation of being the Author of Sin, and yet to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his concurrence with ſecond Cauſes, in producing their defective effects. If the will of the Creature,</hi> ſaith <hi>Scotus,</hi> C. 2. Diſt. 37. Q. 1. <hi>were the total and immediate cauſe of her action, and that God had no immediate effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, but mediate only in reſpect thereof, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101372:21"/>ſome think: It were eaſie according to that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to ſhew how God may be freed from the imputation of being the Author of Sin, and yet to acknowledg his concurrence with ſecond Cauſes, for the producing of their effects: for whether we ſpeak of that which is material or formal in ſin, the will only ſhould be the total cauſe of it, and God ſhould no way be a cauſe of it but mediately, in that he cauſed and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſuch a will, that might at her pleaſure do what ſhe would.</hi> Durandus <hi>ſeemeth to incline to this opinion, ſuppoſing that ſecond Cauſes do bring forth their actions and operations by and of themſelves, and that God no otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth actually to the production of the ſame, but in that he preſerveth the ſecond Cauſes in that being and power of working, which firſt he gave them.</hi> Thus far the moſt Learned Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> of the Church, <hi>B.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 23. <hi>pag.</hi> 121, 122. And yet he adds his diſlike of <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus</hi> opinion in theſe words: <hi>But they that are of ſounder judgment reſolve, that as the light enlightneth the air, and with the air all other inferiour things: ſo God not only giveth being and power of working to the ſecond Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and preſerveth them in the ſame, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them hath an immediate influence into the things that are to be effected by them, &amp;c.</hi> Ibid. p. 122.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What account can be given of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploding our diſtinction between the <hi>material</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101372:21"/>and <hi>formal part of ſin?</hi> [approved of above by Dr. <hi>Field]. Moſt of his way,</hi> (viz. Mr. <hi>Gales</hi>) <hi>mince the buſineſs, and ſay, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence is only to the action, which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; not as ſinful,</hi> ſo Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s <hi>Poſtſc. p.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Except it were affirmed, that it implied a contradiction for God to make ſuch a creature, there is no imaginable pretence, why it ſhould not be admitted he hath done it,</hi> Let. p. 37. and ſubjoins ſoon after, <hi>I muſt confeſs a greater diſpoſition to wonder that ever ſuch a thing ſhould be diſputed, than diſpute ſo plain a caſe,</hi> p. 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> That it is affirmed, Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> cannot ſurely be ignorant; nay, he frees himſelf from that blame. I am not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant what attempts have been made to prove it impoſſible, <hi>p.</hi> 38. but in the interim he incurs another of contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf.</p>
               <p>This Argument, <hi>ab abſurdo,</hi> from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Gods making a creature inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon himſelf, is urged againſt thoſe that deny <hi>immediate concurrence</hi> (and ſo by juſt conſequence <hi>conſervation</hi>) and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As to <hi>mediate concurrence,</hi> 'tis urged for it by <hi>Durandus, That there is no repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncy nor contradiction for God to make a creature that ſhould be able to act without
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101372:22"/>his help [otherwiſe, that is, than by conſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its being and powers].</hi> To this is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Involvere repugnantiam quod creaturae ſit potens,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That it involves a repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and contradiction, that the creature ſhould be able to act independently upon the Creator, as well in reſpect of the created cauſe it ſelf, which hath neceſſarily a power of acting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate and proportionable to its own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as in reſpect of the action or effect flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it; for ſeeing they are Beings by participation, they eſſentially depend upon the firſt Being. Wherefore, as the Divine power cannot produce a Being independent upon him in its Being, ſo nor produce an Agent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent upon him in acting.</hi> Suarez. Met. T. 1. D. 22. n. 16. One egg is not more like another, than <hi>Durandus</hi> Argument to Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s; nor can a more ſolid Anſwer be given thereto, no, though Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> ſhould acknowledg <hi>immediate concurrence,</hi> (as in his <hi>Poſtſc.</hi> he does) of which, in his whole Letter there is <hi>altum ſilentium,</hi> and deny on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Predetermination:</hi> for this Anſwer is a ſhoo that will fit either foot (as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in its place).</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to <hi>conſervation,</hi> the no neceſſity of Gods continual influx to that end ſeems colourably affirmed upon this ground too, <hi>That it is not repugnant to Omnipotency to produce ſuch creatures, as when once made,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101372:22"/>may continue their Being; though the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Agent ceaſe, by which they were produced.</hi> To this Argument <hi>Suarez</hi> alſo fits a rational reply; <hi>Ad amplitudinem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae potentiae ſpectat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It belongs to the amplitude of the Divine Power, that nothing is, nor can be a moment after its production without its influence; and alſo that it have full dominion over all his creatures, and an intrinſick power of annihilating them, by the ſuſpenſion or withholding of his influence,</hi> Suarez. Met. T. 1. D. 21. n. 2, 17.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which is directly to our caſe upon Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s explication of his mind, <hi>that he does really believe Gods immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to all actions of his creatures, both immediatione virtutis &amp; ſuppoſiti, yet not determinative to wicked actions,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 28. we ſhall adventure a demonſtration, that it implies a contradiction for God to make a creature that can act without Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, <hi>i. e.</hi> applying it to action, and to one rather than another action; and 'tis this, that ſuch a creature would be but <hi>ens ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darium,</hi> a <hi>ſecond being;</hi> not <hi>cauſa ſecunda,</hi> a <hi>ſecond cauſe,</hi> or (which is all one) God ſhould be but <hi>ens primum,</hi> not <hi>cauſa prima,</hi> the <hi>firſt Being,</hi> not the <hi>firſt Cauſe;</hi> which I prove thus.</p>
               <p>Arg. 1. If God does concur only by <hi>ſimultaneous concourſe,</hi> and not by <hi>Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101372:23"/>or <hi>previous motion,</hi> then God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the cauſe of the actions of the creatures as they proceed from them. But the <hi>conſequent</hi> is abſurd; and Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> I preſume, will not own it. Therefore ſo is the <hi>Antecedent.</hi> The <hi>Conſequence</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus: God is not by concourſe the cauſe of the actions of the creatures, as thoſe actions proceed from them, becauſe then concourſe muſt be before the action of the creature (for every Phyſical cauſe is before the effect), but the very name <hi>concourſe,</hi> imports a joyning together in the ſame action, as the Maſter and Scholar, whoſe hand is guided in ſhaping the ſame letter. And all conſent, in <hi>concourſe,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does God act before the creature, nor the creature before God, but both together, and at once.</p>
               <p>Arg. 2. To make good the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>He is twice killed, that is killed with his own weapon.</hi> I ſhall retort, Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s two conceſſions upon him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If <hi>there be an immediate concourſe,</hi> then there is a Predetermination, or putting the creature upon action before it acts; or elſe the creature is the firſt mover of it ſelf to action. The <hi>conſequence</hi> is plauſible enough, as depending on this ground, that by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe alone we have no account given us how God and the creature join in one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101372:23"/>action rather than another. As for inſtance, in the ſtate of innocency, when man was incircled with a variety of trees of the Garden, all good and fit for food, whence was it that he will'd to eat of one rather than another. The concourſe of God with <hi>Adam's</hi> will in the election of one (ſuppoſe that in the midſt of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, before the prohibition paſſed upon it) could not determine it to that rather than to any of the reſt, as is plain in external acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Two men lanching a wherry-boat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to the ſame effect; but the one does not determine the other, by lending com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſiſtance to that act. There muſt be therefore a Predetermination in order of nature, though not of time, to that act of <hi>Adam</hi>'s will [ſuppoſed] of eating that tree inſtanced in, to which God concurred. This may be illuſtrated by the example of a Writing-Maſter and his Scholar, wherein there is a concurrence to the action of writing, and its effect the letter written; and alſo a Predetermination, a putting the Scholar upon the action of writing, (not <hi>morally,</hi> for that influence is diſcerned in commanding a Scholar to write by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but <hi>Phyſically,</hi> by putting his hand on the Scholars to write, and to write one letter rather than another. An account how the particular action of any rational
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101372:24"/>creatures will, comes to be determined up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the excluſion of Predetermination, I know none can be given. Not by chance, upon the occaſional ſudden preſentation of an object; becauſe the action is Gods (who is not liable to any ſuch impreſſions) as well as the creatures; not by the <hi>creatures ſelf-determining power,</hi> for that, as ſuch, is indeterminate as to the acts to which we conceive it muſt be ſome way or other determined. And theſe two Propoſitions are ſo evident, that <hi>concurrence immediate</hi> does not determine the will, and that yet it muſt be determined, that <hi>Baronius</hi> himſelf, who is an Antipredeterminant, does acknowledg both, <hi>Met.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 66. and he does ſuggeſt a reaſon againſt any neceſſity laid upon a thing by Divine Preſcience, which we will accept of for a neceſſity of Divine Predetermination to the acts of the will. <hi>Illud ſolum imponit neceſſitatem alicui rei, quod eſt prima ratio cur illa res non potuit non evenire,</hi> i. e. <hi>That alone impoſes neceſſity upon any thing which is the firſt reaſon or cauſe why that thing could not but fall out.</hi> Baron. Met. 7, 12. D. 2. n. 59. [which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that it excludes not the liberty of mans will, ſhall be cleared in due time].</p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, from the neceſſity conceded by Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> of <hi>immediate concourſe and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination to the production of good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101372:24"/>we ſhall infer the neceſſity of both to all actions: This neceſſity muſt take its riſe either from ſomething common to all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or peculiar to good actions. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving the latter, will be the fixing the former in its due place. In order hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, we muſt conſider that grace is an habit ſeated in the natural faculties, and fitting them for good actions; which as it was concreated with them in innocency; ſo in the lapſed eſtate it is re-created, or created again by infuſion: which <hi>infuſion</hi> is not <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination:</hi> for this latter ſtill preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the former. There muſt be grace in habit before it can be acted. Now then the Query is, whether the <hi>terminus</hi> of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination be the habit or the faculties; not the <hi>habit,</hi> for that is a Quality that <hi>meliorates</hi> the faculties, and ſo the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>in genere morali,</hi> and cannot be put upon action, or one rather than another, but <hi>mediante potentia,</hi> by the intervention of the power or faculty in which the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious habit reſides. It muſt then be the <hi>faculties;</hi> the will for inſtance (for of that is the grand inquiry), for otherwiſe (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing what has been owned, that holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits fit the will for holy volitions and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litions) in what degree the habits are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, in that the will may act without Predetermination, and produce ſincerely
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101372:25"/>good actions as it pleaſe, as long as theſe good <hi>actions are done by a power derived originally from it,</hi> [which is Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s Hypotheſis, and judged by him <hi>ſufficient to ſalve the rights and priviledge of the firſt cauſe, with reference to forbidden actions,</hi> Let. p. 36. [and I ſee not, why not as well with reference to commanded actions]. The reſult of this ratiocination will be, that if it be the indetermination of the powers to individual actions that makes an excitation of them to one rather than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other neceſſary; and the poſſibility of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contained in the powers, that makes the reducing of that poſſibility to action no leſs neceſſary to good actions, then the conſequence ſeems immovable, that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination in its two Branches is alike neceſſary to all actions, even when they flow from a will tainted with vicious ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits and inclinations. <hi>Quod erat demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrandum</hi> And to me this Argument ſeems to carry along with it <hi>triumphant evidence,</hi> (to borrow one of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s lofty Epithetes, <hi>Let. p.</hi> 62.) my fancy labours under ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable poverty as to be unable to ſupply me with any evaſion.</p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s phraſe of <hi>impelling,</hi> by which he intends <hi>compelling,</hi> we ſhall refer the word and thing to the Head, where it will moſt properly fall under ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101372:25"/>In the interim, let us attend to what he ſubjoins.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>I confeſs a diſpoſition to wonder that a matter whereupon all moral Government de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, both humane and divine, ſhould not have been determined at the firſt ſight,</hi> Let. p. 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Theſe words imply, that all moral Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is rendred ludicrous, and a meer Pageantry by the Doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination; but upon what Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> magiſterially enough, takes for granted, but does not once make an offer of proving, that the will is hindered by <hi>Gods own ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible counter-action,</hi> p. 37. from yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience to ſuch Government: But if I live till that be proved, my age will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly exceed <hi>Methuſelahs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> adds, <hi>The notion of the goodneſs and righteouſneſs of God, methinks ſhould ſtick ſo cloſe to our minds, and create ſuch a ſenſe in our ſouls, as ſhould be infinitely dearer to us than all our ſenſes and powers. And that we ſhould rather chuſe to have our ſight, hearing, and motive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and what not beſides diſputed, or even torn from us, than ever ſuffer our ſelves to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed into a belief, that the Holy and Good God ſhould irreſiſtibly determine the wills of men to, and puniſh the ſame thing,</hi> Let. p. 19.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101372:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The ſum of the Argument, though accompanied with a long train of fine words, is, that Predetermination to ſinful actions croſſes the natural notions of mankind concerning Gods Goodneſs and Holineſs. To which we return.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is not the leaſt colour for any ſuch conſequence from our Doctrine, but upon ſuppoſition of two things; which Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> would faſten upon us, but we diſown.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>God predetermines to ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in concreto,</hi> i e. to the natural action, and the ſinfulneſs of it: which we conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny: for though we own it a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd province to anſwer all objections that may be ſtarted againſt this partition made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the one and the other, as to Gods influence, which we affirm as to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>the action,</hi> and deny, as to the latter, <hi>the ſinfulneſs of it:</hi> yet 'we doubt not (in its ſeaſon) to evince theſe two things, that God is the Author, and conſequently the Predeterminer of all the actions of rational creatures, (for as to irrational, though we include them, yet the Queſtion not being of them, we ſhall not intermeddle with them); and that God is not the Author of the ſinfulneſs, and ſo not the Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner thereof. And then as to the <hi>modus,</hi> or manner of Gods influence, ſo as to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101372:26"/>theſe that are ſo neerly conjoined in ſinful creatures, we ſhall be leſs ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, at leaſt with reſpect to Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s ſatisfaction, who has profeſſed that he <hi>can more eaſily be ſatisfied, to be ignorant of the modus,</hi> [i. e. manner], <hi>or medium,</hi> [i. e. the mean] <hi>of Gods knowledg, whileſt he is ſure of the thing; and he knows not why any ſober minded man might not be ſo too, while we muſt all be content to be ignorant of the manner, yea, of the nature too of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand things beſides, when, that ſuch things there are, we have no doubt. And when there are few things about which we can with leſs diſadvantage ſuffer our being ignorant, or with leſs diſreputation profeſs to be ſo,</hi> Let. p. 49, 50. And if this Argumentation be true, in reference to Divine acts in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral (as there is no reaſon why it ſhould be limited to Gods knowledg only, and himſelf extends it beyond that); I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> has againſt his will given us the cauſe; for that God is not the Author of ſin (our laſt propoſition) he every where affirms as well as we. That God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all the actions of rational creatures, he grants too; or elſe his words are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible, and we have cauſe to quarrel with him, (as he did with <hi>Perſius,</hi> a crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Poet), <hi>ſi non vult intelligi, cur vult legi,</hi> i. e. If he would not be underſtood,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101372:27"/>why would he be read, (an end that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is preſumed to intend that writes), theſe words, I mean, <hi>This active providence of God about all the actions of men, conſiſts not meerly in giving them the natural pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whereby they can work of themſelves, but in a real influence upon thoſe powers,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 39. By which laſt clauſe, if he intends <hi>reducing them to act</hi> (as his phraſe is, <hi>ibid.</hi>) we are perfectly agreed ſo far; and the remaining diſagreement will be but about the <hi>modus</hi> or <hi>manner,</hi> how God affords a real influence upon the powers defiled with ſin, and yet none upon the ſin it ſelf. And of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his he and I being both (I hope) ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minded men, may well be content to be ignorant, as long as we are ſure of the thing. But I fear I reckon without my Hoſt, and ſo muſt reckon again; I mean, that Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> will not ſtand to my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primize of the difference between us, though I ſee not why he ſhould not, if he will be but a man of his word, ſtand, that is, to his own Aſſertions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our Doctrine cannot be accuſed of a confederacy, to raze out the impreſſions of Gods Holineſs upon humane nature; but upon this ſuppoſition alſo, <hi>That God does irreſiſtibly determine the wills of men to that which he puniſhes men for,</hi> viz. <hi>to ſin,</hi> which is a brat we are not bound to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101372:27"/>For we neither own <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> nor <hi>reſiſtible</hi> determination of mans will to ſin, as ſuch; nor do we acknowledg any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the will at all to be <hi>irreſiſtible,</hi> if he takes that term for equivalent to <hi>compulſory;</hi> which if he do not, it will be neither a friend to him, nor foe to us.</p>
               <p>We might alſo obſerve upon his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical amplifications of his Argument, that he ſeems to be no ill-willer to <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi> For if <hi>the natural notions of Gods goodneſs ſhould be infinitely dearer to us than our ſenſes,</hi> I ſee not why the notion of Gods ſincerity, that he means as he ſpeaks, ſhould not challenge a ſhare in our indear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and ſo why, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> ſhould not aſſure us, that the bread is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated, though our ſenſes, ſight, taſte, feeling, join in a common teſtimony, that it remains bread after conſecration, as well as before: not that I charge him with that <hi>Popiſh ridicule,</hi> but I would have him take notice how dangerous ſometimes an affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of embelliſhments of ſpeech may prove, by leaving him that is guilty of it, at the mercy of his Antagoniſt, in deducing ſuch inferences from them, as can neither be ſafely admitted, nor creditably turned off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> complains of the <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101372:28"/>and impotency of our defence</hi> againſt the forenamed charge, <hi>that God makes a Law, and neceſſitates the violation of it;</hi> when it is no more than, <hi>That man is under the Law, and God above it,</hi> Let. p. 40, 41. and he affirms, <hi>that a tender ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>will not be relieved or eaſed by the thin Sophiſtry of only a colluſive ambiguity in the word Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s candour did but bear any tolerable proportion to his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, he would never have thus repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented our Anſwer. For the truth is, this Anſwer is not given by the <hi>Predeterminants</hi> to that objection to which he applies it (as is plain enough, becauſe we always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem our ſelves unconcerned in the charge of repreſenting God as neceſſitating the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of his own Law), but to another, <hi>(viz.) that God ſins when he produces that action with man, which to man is ſin,</hi> (which Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> who in words at leaſt owns <hi>immediate concurrence</hi> to all actions as well we, is therefore equally concerned to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer). For the proof of this, I ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who (after he had told us, it was only <hi>Zuinglius</hi>'s Anſwer to the ſame Objection that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> fits it to; adds with the peril of his reputation), <hi>Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam tamen aliorum quorundam, &amp;c.</hi> i. e. <hi>That it was the opinion of others alſo, who
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101372:28"/>though they agreed not with</hi> Zuinglius, <hi>in teaching that God impels men to ſin, yet they uſe no other medium to evince how God does not ſin, when he produces that action with man, which to man is ſin, than that God is bound by no Law, and nothing is ſin but a tranſgreſſion of a Law,</hi> Bell de Amiſſ. Gr. l. 2. c. 18. Yet withal I deny not, but 'tis alſo applied to that Objection, that God ſins, if he does determine to that action, to which ſin inſeparably cleaves. But yet <hi>the neceſſitation of the violation of the Law,</hi> is no way concerned in the objection.</p>
               <p>What now is become of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s charge of <hi>thin Sophiſtry,</hi> and <hi>colluſive am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity,</hi> when we deny God to be under a <hi>Law,</hi> in the ſame ſignification of the word, wherein we affirm it of man, (<hi>viz.</hi> as Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> expreſſes it), <hi>For the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pleaſure of a Ruler to a Subject,</hi> p. 41. This charge diſproved, we yet grant what Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> objects; that the term <hi>Law,</hi> as noting <hi>an habitual principle, and rule of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after one ſteady tenour, in which ſenſe the perfect rectitude of Gods nature is an eternal Law to him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let. p.</hi> 41, 42, is yet an Argument againſt our opinion upon Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that thereby the creature is neceſſitated to ſin: but that he hath neither attempted, nor ever will be able to prove. If proof could be made
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101372:29"/>that the conſequence were natural, we ſhould not know how to decline the force of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>'s grave Argumentation upon Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s ground, <hi>Licet deo non ſit poſita Lex ab aliquo ſuperiore Legiſlatore, tamen ſua ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia eſt ipſi Lex,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e. Though God be not under a Law given him by a ſuperiour Legiſlatour, yet his own wiſdom is a Law to him; and as</hi> Zuinglius <hi>himſelf teaches us, That what a Law is to us, that is Gods own nature to him. God is therefore no leſs bound, not to act repugnantly to his own wiſdom and nature, than men are bound not to act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantly to the Law of God. Wherefore, if God ſhould impel</hi> [Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s phraſe], <hi>men to theſe things, which are contrary to the Eternal Law, and to his own nature and wiſdom, as to Adultery, his will were evil, becauſe repugnant to the right rule of divine wiſdom, and God ſhould deny himſelf, which cannot be (as the Apoſtle ſays).</hi> Thus far <hi>Bellarmine, ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> concludes, <hi>What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is there in that dream, [of the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed poſſibility of Gods making a reaſonable creature with an innocent averſion to himſelf]. For what can be ſuppoſed more repugnant? or what more impertinent? If innocent, how were it puniſhable? A Law already made in the caſe, how can it be innocent?</hi> Let. p. 42.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:101372:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> leaves us wholly at a loſs, who it is, that with this dream hath attempted <hi>to relieve a pious and ſober mind, cloſely urged with the horrour of ſo black a conception of God, that he does firſt irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly determine mens will to, and then puniſh them for the hatred of his bleſſed ſelf,</hi> (as he tragically, but <hi>falſely</hi> repreſents our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion), <hi>p.</hi> 40. I ſay <hi>falſely,</hi> for God does not puniſh that natural paſſion we call ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, which himſelf, as firſt Cauſe, applies the ſecond to the production of; nor does God determine the will to that natural paſſion, its elicite act, <hi>irreſiſtibly,</hi> in his ſenſe <hi>forcibly.</hi> But as <hi>Auſtin</hi> long ago, of Gods influence upon good actions; [ſo ſay we of bad] God acts <hi>Omnipotenter pro te, ſuaviter pro me, Omnipotently according to his own nature, but ſweetly according to ours,</hi> (as ſhall be fully cleared in its place). If any particular perſon of our judgment in the main, ſhall propoſe an argument li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to exception, I ſee not that we are obliged to defend it. But as Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> introduces it, it ſeems to be repreſented as a common extravagancy of the Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minants, which I am ſure it is not; nor does Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> labour under a ſurguedry of candour, in a bare preſentation of this ſuppoſition, without its application to the Queſtion. Both which, becauſe Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101372:30"/>neglected, I think not my ſelf obliged to give the Reader an account of, but ſhall diſmiſs it without any adoe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. The ſecond preſſing and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Argument of ours which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats, <hi>That God does predetermine ſinful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as actions, otherwiſe it were impoſſible for God to foreknow the ſinful actions of men (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whereof he hath foretold) if their futuriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were a meer contingency, and depended on the uncertain will of the ſubordinate agent, not determined by the ſupream agent [God.]</hi> Let. p. 35, 36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which Argument, this is the ſum of his Anſwer, <hi>That this ſuppoſed inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Will in reference to wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d actions, is far from being capable of inferring any thing more than that we are left ignorant of the way how he foreknows them, which is a ſmall inconvenience, and manifeſt abſurdity not to ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nowledg the like in many caſes, ſeeing God does many things, whereof the manner how he does them we can neither explicate nor underſtand.</hi> Let. p. 47, 48.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. To which I reply, That the way how God foreknows future contingencies, is in his own Decree, at leaſt as to ſuch which he hath decreed. For I cannot divine what can be oppoſed to this Propoſition, That what God hath decreed he foreknows in his own Decree, (though it ſhould be granted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101372:30"/>that he foreknows them alſo antecedently to his own Decree in ſome manner, which we can neither explicate nor underſtand.) Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that then for granted till it be denied, I think Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath much overſhot himſelf in denying univerſally our knowledg of the way how God foreknows future contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. For either he muſt exclude <hi>the good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which he grants <hi>God predetermines men to,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 39. yea, and <hi>all actions</hi> of free agents to which he acknowledges God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords <hi>immediate concourſe,</hi> p. 28. from being <hi>Contingencies;</hi> (which himſelf as well as we, ſuppoſe in the whole controverſie now agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) Or deny that they fall under Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; (which is too abſurd, becauſe there's nothing more evident than that what God does in time, he decreed to do from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) Or if he grants both, then it roundly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that God foreknew thoſe acts of the Creatures which in time he did either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determine to, or concur with; and ſuch are all the actions of men disjunctively.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 2. We ſhall prove that God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knows all future contingencies in his own Decree, and conſequently the ſinful actions of men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.9, 10, <hi>I am God, and there is none like me, declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times the things that are not yet done, ſaying, my
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101372:31"/>counſel ſhall ſtand, and I will do all my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> Upon which Scripture the <hi>Incomparable Calvin,</hi> (ſo I call him in compliance with the very Learned <hi>Andrews,</hi> (ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>'s admonition), that he was a man never to be named without the addition of ſome title of Honour) thus gloſſes, <hi>Neque ſolum ejus praeſcientiam hic commendat,</hi> &amp;c. i.e. <hi>Neither does God only here commend his own Preſcience, but he affirms that he had te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the Prophets what he had decreed. For there were no certainty, nor firmneſs in the Predictions, or Propheſies, unleſs the ſame God who foretells this or that thing would come to paſs, had the event of things in his own hand.</hi> As to which words we may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerve:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The form of the expreſſion:</hi> two Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes are here applied by God to himſelf, Wiſdom and Soveraignty or liberty of Will, and a common adjunct of both, Immutability, [or we may call it a common effect, the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the event] that what God does wiſely and freely determine or decree within himſelf, ſhall certainly come to paſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The extent of it,</hi> that it refers to all thoſe things which it was Gods peculiar certainly to foreknow, <hi>viz.</hi> all that ſhould certainly come to paſs. For as <hi>Judicious Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> obſerves upon <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Poſteaquam Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>After that the Prophet had ſpoken
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101372:31"/>of the Preſcience of God, he accommodates the general expreſſion he had uſed to his preſent purpoſe, to comfort the</hi> Jews <hi>in hopes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of their Captivity by Cyrus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The argument which is couched in them,</hi> to evince the certainty of Gods foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of what he did predict, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the events predicted were the reſult of his Wiſdom and Pleaſure, or of his own wiſe Decrees.</p>
               <p>And now to draw down this General to the particular in queſtion, <hi>Whether God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knows ſinful actions in his own Decree.</hi> And for the proof of the affirmative I ſhall quote but that place, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.28, compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.23, <hi>For to do whatſoever thy hand and thy counſel determined before to be done.</hi> So the former place, <hi>Him being delivered by the determinate counſel and foreknowledg of God, ye have taken and by wicked hands have crucified and ſlain.</hi> So the latter; both ſpeaking of the moſt wicked action that ever was done in the world, the putting the Lord of Life to death. To the former place the <hi>Learned Calvin</hi> ſays, <hi>They who acknowledg only the Preſcience of God, but do not confeſs that all things are managed by Gods will, are eaſily convinced by theſe words, that God hath foreordained that to be done which is done.</hi> To the latter place the Learned Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> (now newly deceaſed, to the great grief of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101372:32"/>Pious &amp; Learned Men) affords a notable gloſs, (which I eſpecially recommend to Mr <hi>H.</hi> for the friendſhip ſake between the Doctor and him, in his Comment on <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13. p. 101. <hi>Many who grant Preſcience, deny Preordination,</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> the Decree, whereof Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the execution; So I underſtand him] <hi>leſt they ſhould make God the Author of Sin: but theſe fear where no fear is. The Scripture ſpeaketh roundly, aſcribing both to God,</hi> Act. 2.23. [<hi>N. B.</hi>] Peter <hi>ſaith not only</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>by the foreknowledg; but</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>determinate counſel; which implieth a poſitive Decree.</hi> So far he: and for ought I know conſonantly to the conſtant ſenſe of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſm, till now of late that it grows weary of it ſelf, if we may judg of its preſent humour by Mr <hi>H.</hi> and Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) And by theſe ſound Interpretations we may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judg, whether Mr. <hi>H.</hi>'s gloſs upon <hi>Act.</hi> 4.28. doth not corrupt the Text. Let us hear it, if our patience can bear ſuch an exerciſe. <hi>That is, God foreſeeing wicked hands would be prompt and read for this tragick enterpriſe, his Soveraign power and wiſe counſel concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his foreknowledg, ſo only, and not with leſs latitude, to define or determine the bounds and limits of that malignity, than to let it proceed unto this execution,</hi> Let. p. 29. And ſoon after, <hi>Which purpoſe</hi> (viz.) <hi>of Chriſts to give himſelf to be a propitiation
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101372:32"/>for the ſins of men by dying, it was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned [by God] not to hinder prepared hands to execute in this way,</hi> p. 30. Theſe words plainly imply a denial of Gods foreknowledg of the Death of Chriſt, as conſequent to his Decree of that event, (which is ſufficiently confirmed by the Scriptures now quoted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that denial) and they imply an affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a foreknowledg of Chriſts Death an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to Gods Decree; and ſo make a confuſion (where a diſtinction ought to be kept) between Gods foreknowledg of <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibles</hi> and <hi>futures;</hi> or of what <hi>may,</hi> and of what <hi>ſhall</hi> come to paſs; and run Mr. <hi>H.</hi> into this abſurdity, to deny that any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree paſſed upon the Death of Chriſt at all. For to what end ſhould he paſs a Decree, if he foreknew it would come to paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it? I cannot conceive how Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can rid his hands of this abſurdity, unleſs he ſhall affirm, the <hi>paſſion,</hi> but not the <hi>action,</hi> the death of Chriſt, but not their agency who put him to death was the object of Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. But then <hi>Auſtin</hi> will correct him by his gloſs upon that Text, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17, <hi>For it is better, if the will of God be ſo, that ye ſuffer for well-doing than for evil doing. Sancti affliguntur ſecundum Dei voluntatem, &amp;c.</hi> i.e. <hi>The Saints are afflicted according to the will of God, but they cannot ſuffer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs wicked men act. He that wills the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101372:33"/>wills the action.</hi> Aug. in Enchir. c. 100. And the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> will fall foul upon him with his naxim, <hi>Actio &amp; Paſſio ſunt idem motus.</hi> i.e. <hi>Action and Paſſion are one and the ſame motion.</hi> And differ but as the way from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>York,</hi> and from <hi>York</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> and but as the aſcent and deſcent of the ſame Hill. And ſo it cannot be preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with any colour, that the Decree of God includes the <hi>Paſsion</hi> of Chriſt, and excludes the <hi>Jews</hi> and Gentiles action about it. I will diſmiſs Mr. <hi>H.</hi> as to this Text without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exagitation, when I have but minded him of a paſſage of the acute <hi>Twiſſe,</hi> (who I preſume, is one of thoſe <hi>pious and learned men, to whom his reverence is not extinguiſhed, notwithſtanding the badneſs of their opinion about Predetermination,</hi> Poſt. p. 49.) <hi>Dictata iſta Jeſuitica,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thoſe Jeſuitical dictates of the foreſeen determination of the humane will before Gods Decree, are not the dictates diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentium Theologorum, ſed ſomniantium.</hi> i.e. <hi>Of Divines diſputing, but dreaming.</hi> Twiſſ. Vind. Gr. L. 2. p. 1. Digr. 2. c. 1. p. 31. And ſo I have cried you quittance, <hi>one dream for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi> [Let. p. 42.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. By reaſon we ſhall demonſtrate, that Gods foreknowledg of all future contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies depend upon his Decree. And I ſhall chuſe to borrow (becauſe I have none of my own better) that of Dr. <hi>Twiſſe,</hi> which hath
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101372:33"/>been eſteemed irrefragable, ſays the Learned <hi>Strangius,</hi> who yet oppoſes it, but not with ſtrength enough to overthrow it; and hath done us the favour to reduce the whole proceſs of the Argumentation into form. <hi>De Vol. Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 626.</p>
               <p>Arg. 1. <hi>What is future only by the Decree of God, that God neceſſarily foreknew by his Decree. But every future contingent is future only by the Decree of God.</hi> Ergo, <hi>every fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contingent did God neceſſarily foreknow by his Decree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Minor</hi> proved. <hi>That which is fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Eternity, that is not future but by Gods Decree. But every future contingent is future from Eternity.</hi> Ergo, <hi>every future contingent is future only by the Decree of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Major</hi> of the laſt Syllogiſm proved. <hi>That which from Eternity paſſed out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a thing poſſible, into the condition of a thing future, that is not future but by Gods Decree. But that which is future from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity did paſs from Eternity out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a thing poſſible into the condition of a thing future.</hi> Ergo, <hi>That which is future from Eternity is not future but by Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Major</hi> of the laſt Syllogiſm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>That which from Eternity paſſed out of the condition of a thing poſſible into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101372:34"/>of a thing future, had for the cauſe of that paſſage the Decree of God, or no cauſe at all. But it cannot be ſaid it had no cauſe at all.</hi> Ergo, <hi>only the Decree of God was the cauſe of that paſſage out of the condition of a thing poſſible into the condition of a thing future.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Minor</hi> of the laſt Syllogiſm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Future contingents are either future in their own nature, or not future but by ſome cauſe determining their indifferent nature. But future contingents are not future in their own nature; elſe it would follow, that they ſhould be always future, and never become preſent. For what agrees to any thing of its own nature, agrees to it inſeparably.</hi> Ergo, <hi>future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingents muſt needs be future from ſome cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>Major</hi> of the ſame fourth Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm proved. <hi>If there be any cauſe why any thing paſſeth from Eternity out of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a poſſible thing into the condition of a future, that cauſe muſt be either ſomething without God, or in God; and if in God, either that cauſe ſhall be the eſſence of God, or the knowledg of God, or the will and decree of God. But the cauſe of any thing becoming of poſsible future, is neither any thing without God, nor the eſſence or the knowledg of God.</hi> Ergo, <hi>it is only the will or decree of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Minor</hi> of the laſt Syllogiſm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101372:34"/>by parts. <hi>For firſt, nothing out of God could be the cauſe, becauſe that paſſage (which they call futurition) was made from eternity, and therefore the cauſe thereof muſt be from eternity. But nothing is eternal beſides God. Nor can the knowledg of God be the cauſe; for that ſevered from his will, doth rather ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, than make things future. Moreover, if the Eſſence of God were the cauſe of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of things from poſſibility to futurity, it muſt either be ſaid to be the cauſe as acting ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily or freely. Not the former, for then all future things would fall out neceſſarily, and none would fall out contingently and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But God in things to be created, or created, hath done, nor doth any thing by neceſſity of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but freely. If the Eſſence of God be ſaid to be the cauſe of the paſſage of things from poſſibility into futurity, as acting freely, this is to grant, that the will of God and the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination thereof is the cauſe why any contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent from eternity paſſeth out of the condition of an indifferent thing to be or not to be, into the condition of a thing future, or to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the futurition of it. It remains therefore that the Decree of God, or the Decreeing will of God, be alone the cauſe of futurition (if you will admit the phraſe) and of its effect.</hi> Thus far Dr. <hi>Twiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire the Reader to take notice, That though I have a great reverence for Dr.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101372:35"/>
                  <hi>Twiſſe,</hi> and do judg the proceſs of the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Argument invincible as to the main; yet I am not clear in my apprehenſion, that the third Syllogiſm is in ſenſe different from the ſecond, (as <hi>Strangius</hi> objects againſt it with ſome probability.) Nor yet do I whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſlike <hi>Strangius</hi> his alteration of the terms of both the <hi>Majors</hi> of the ſecond and third <hi>Syllogiſm,</hi> thus: <hi>That which from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was poſsible ſo, as that it alſo had the condition of a thing future, its futurition is from the Decree of God. But every future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent was from eternity poſsible ſo, as that it alſo had the condition of a thing future.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the futurition of every future contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent is from the Decree of God.</hi> And then the fourth Syllogiſm will be the proof of the Major of the ſecond, (leaving out the third) and the words muſt be the ſame; and ſo the argument runs on without any further rub, unleſs perhaps the reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the fifth Syllogiſm, <hi>Why contingent things are not future in their own nature,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it would follow, <hi>that they ſhould be always future, and never become preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For I confeſs ingenuouſly, that I cannot anſwer <hi>Strangius</hi> contrary conſequent from that antecedent; <hi>That if future contingents were neceſſarily future, whether in their own nature, or in reſpect of any other cauſe, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of God, they muſt neceſſarily be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101372:35"/>ſome time or other. For to be future is nothing elſe than that a thing ſhould ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time be preſent.</hi> Strang. p. 630.</p>
               <p>And theſe alterations (though I will not poſitively aſſert to be needful, as not having had time to examine <hi>Strangius</hi> throughly ſince he came to my hands, (which was long after Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Letter and Poſtſcript came out,) yet I am the more willing to admit, that I may in part wipe off the aſperſion Mr. <hi>H.</hi> caſts upon many of us, who hold Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, <hi>That whatſoever ſtrength there may be in arguments and replys to and fro in this matter, that which hath too apparently had greateſt actual efficacy with many, hath been the authority and name of this and that man of reputation.</hi> Let. p. 42.</p>
               <p>As to all the reſt of the Doctor's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (if I be not a partial judg of my own abilities, an infirmity of lapſed humane nature, which I cannot challenge an exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from,) I ſeem to my ſelf able to anſwer <hi>Strangius</hi>'s ſubtil evaſions, and ſhould will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly have done it, but that I doubt not but I ſhall meet with them in Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s threatened Rejoinder, in which I expect Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhould anſwer diſtinctly, by denial or diſtinction, to ſome Propoſition in theſe Syllogiſms; and then let him rhetoricate as he pleaſes in the amplification.</p>
               <p>We have now diſpatched the two Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101372:36"/>in the <hi>Letter,</hi> there remain three in the <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> cited out of Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s <hi>Anim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adverſions upon the Letter;</hi> which, though modeſtly propoſed by way of Queſtion, will conſtringe our Learned Adverſary.</p>
               <p>Arg. 3. <hi>Whether there be any action of man on earth ſo good, which hath not ſome mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſin in it? And if God concur to the ſubſtrate matter of it as good, muſt he not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily concur to the ſubſtrate matter as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? for is not the ſubſtrate matter of the act, both as good and ſinful the ſame?</hi> Poſtſcr. p. 32.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Anſw. 1. <hi>It ſeems then that God doth concur to the matter of an action as ſinful; which is honeſtly acknowledged, ſince by his principles it cannot be denied: though moſt of his way mince the buſineſs, and ſay, the concurrence is only to the action which is ſinful, not as ſinful.</hi> Ibid. &amp; pag. 33. So Mr. <hi>H.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> miſrepreſents Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s meaning: for it is not, that God concurs to the ſinfulneſs of the action, but to the action; which though phyſically one indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual action, yet is morally diverſified in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its conformity and difformity to the Law of God: ſo that conſidering the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral action <hi>in concreto,</hi> with the good or evil adhering to it, it is no leſs true, that God concurs to the action that hath evil adhering
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101372:36"/>to it, than that he concurs to the action that hath good adhering to it. This premiſed, to the fault he finds with the diſtinction, I anſwer, that I doubt he muſt recur to it himſelf, when he is preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to know how Gods concurrence immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to actions ſinful will free him from the imputation of being the Author of Sin: yea, worſe than ſo, I cannot imagine, but that as to thoſe actions, which he calls in themſelves ſinful, he muſt own what he would faſten upon Mr. <hi>Gale,</hi> that God doth immediately concur to the matter of an action as ſinful; <hi>for 'tis impoſsible to ſeparate the malignity thereof from an intrinſecally evil action,</hi> (as he tells us) <hi>Let. p.</hi> 33. [of which hereafter.)</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Anſw. 2. <hi>This I am to conſider as an argument for Gods Predeterminative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence to wicked actions. And thus it muſt be conceived, that if God concur by determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive influence to the imperfectly good actions of faith, love,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>therefore to the acts of enmity againſt himſelf, curſing, idolatry,</hi> &amp;c. To which (beſides an unſeemly ſcoff, <hi>is it not a mighty conſequence?</hi>) Mr. <hi>H.</hi> anſwers divers things, as reaſons for the denial of the conſequence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is infirm, becauſe <hi>the actions</hi> in the antecedent <hi>are good, quoad ſubſtantiam,</hi> but theſe in the conſequent <hi>are in the ſubſtance of them evil.</hi> Poſt. p. 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 1. Mr. <hi>Gale</hi> doth not limit wicked
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101372:37"/>actions to thoſe that are in the ſubſtance of them evil, but ampliates the term to all whatſoever ſo that ſuppoſing the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence were not good to ſuch actions as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> inſtanceth in; yet it may be good to thoſe actions that are evil, <hi>quoad finem &amp; circumſtantias,</hi> as to the end and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For inſtance, to be hoſpitable, or chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table out of vain-glory, to be reading the Scriptures at home, when we ſhould attend upon publick worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſeems to yield it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I am not yet convinced that there are any actions evil, <hi>quoad ſubſtantiam.</hi> And it is a wonder to me, that our Learned Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt ſhould exact of us an implicite faith of that Poſition. It ill becomes his generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo baſely to beg the queſtion. Let him prove that, and I will be his Proſelyte as to antipredetermination of ſuch actions. But becauſe he neglecteth the duty he owes to his Hypotheſis, I will perform mine to my own anon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> denies the conſequence by an argument <hi>a pari; That we our ſelves can in a remoter kind concur to the actions of others, yet it doth not follow, that becauſe we may aſſord our leading concurrence to actions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly good, that therefore we may afford it to thoſe that are down right evil; becauſe to prayer, therefore to curſing and ſwearing,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101372:37"/>and then ruin men for the actions we have induced them unto.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. &amp; p. 34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. In general 'tis unſafe arguing <hi>a pari,</hi> from the creature to God; that what the former may not do, neither may the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The creature is bound to hinder all the ſin that he can; but if God were under ſuch an obligation, there would not only have been ſo much ſin as the world affords, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed none at all. And you your ſelf diſcourſe at large of the <hi>incongruity of an univerſal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminative influence to good actions;</hi> which yet would have made an admirable Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis of all the Sinners in the world into Saints; (at leaſt if in thoſe expreſſions you include, <hi>infuſion of grace,</hi> which <hi>divine Predetermination</hi> of good actions preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as I have proved before.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. If your arguing be forcible as to this inſtance, I ſee not, but you reflect as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon God by the <hi>immediate concurrence</hi> you grant <hi>to all actions of the Creatures,</hi> Poſt. p. 28. For will it not follow, that God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords men a leading concurrence to actions down-right evil, and then ruins them for thoſe actions, which were as much his as theirs? I am too dull to imagine how you can extricate your ſelf, but by eating your words, and diſtinguiſhing of concurrence, as you do of Predetermination; that God concurs to actions that are imperfectly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101372:38"/>good, but not to thoſe that are down-right evil.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s anſwer touches not the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s argument, which is to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince upon Mr. H's own aſſertion, that as God predetermines to actions imperfectly good; ſo by the like reaſon he may predetermine to actions that are perfectly evil. And the ground of the conſequence is this, that if in actions imperfectly good, the evil and the good of the actions are ſo divided between the creature and God, that only the former is the Creatures, and the latter Gods; whilſt yet the natural actions themſelves are common to both, to God as the firſt, to the Creature as the ſecond cauſe; why may not we infer that in actions perfectly evil, the action is common to God and the Creature, but the evil of it, the Creatures peculiar, and no more chargeable upon God, than in the other inſtance. And this I take for an irrefragable Argument, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> which if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can ſatisfie, I am ſilenced.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is an unaccountable inadvertency, (for to ſalve his honour, ſo I will call it, rather than a ſlip of Judgment) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>curſing</hi> and <hi>ſwearing</hi> for inſtances of <hi>actions down-right,</hi> or <hi>for the ſubſtance of them evil.</hi> I thought that <hi>Davids</hi> frequent <hi>curſing</hi> of wicked men in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101372:38"/>
                  <hi>Pauls ſwearing, Before God I lye not,</hi> Gal. 1.20. had not paſſed under ſo bad a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; but did reſt aſſured, that (as the actions in themſelves are capable, ſo in them) they were hallowed by their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and end.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To what end Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> cloſes with this clauſe, <hi>And then ruine men for the actions we have induced them to,</hi> is not hard to conjecture <hi>(viz.)</hi> to inſinuate, that our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine repreſents God under the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter with the Devil, who induces men to ſin, and then torments them for it. But what is ſaid untruly (as well as Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) of the Devil, is verified of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>That it is not ſo black as it is paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> indeed tells Mr. <hi>Gale,</hi> you'l ſay <hi>God may rather,</hi> and adds as his own ſenſe, <hi>But ſure he can do ſo much leſs than you,</hi> p. 34. This ſuggeſtion deſerves a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer animadverſion than I ſhall make upon it. In general, I ſay 'tis <hi>an odious ſlander.</hi> For we in no ſenſe aſſert that God indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces men to wicked actions, not <hi>morally,</hi> for we conſtantly affirm, that his commands, threats, are all againſt it; not <hi>Phyſically,</hi> for ſo he determines men to actions, not to the wickedneſs of them, nor does he ruine men for what he contributes by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination, or immediate concurrence to the Production of <hi>(viz.)</hi> the natural
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101372:39"/>actions he moves to and joins in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> denies the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from the evidence of two Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures compared, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.6. p. 35. but (which is ſtrange) hath not directed us how he infers from them the denial of Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s conſequence, or how they ſhew a difference between the warrantableneſs of Gods concurring to the <hi>ſubſtrate matter of an action as good, which tends to mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and bleſſedneſs, and to the ſubſtrate matter of all their evil actions [which tend to their ruine and miſery];</hi> we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gueſs at it as well as we can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The former Scripture hath theſe words, <hi>Is it lawful on the ſabbath days to do good or to do evil, to ſave life or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy?</hi> The latter theſe, <hi>O Iſrael, thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thine help:</hi> From the former Scripture, I preſume, thus he argues: If it be unlawful to man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy life, then it is unlawful to God. But the antecedent is true, therefore the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. And he proves the conſequence by the latter Scripture, by this Enthymeme; Gods word is to help man. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is unlawful for him to deſtroy. And this, <hi>viz.</hi> that man deſtroys himſelf. <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for God to deſtroy him. To which, I return,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>antecedent</hi> or <hi>minor</hi> of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101372:39"/>firſt Syllogiſm, is not true univerſally, for for it is not unlawful for man to deſtroy life, <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> i.e. in ſelf-defence; but it muſt be limited to Homicide or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which notes not barely the act of deſtroying life, but involves with it a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſity, or that act done in caſes prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the divine Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Suppoſe it were, yet I deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and you cannot be any whit-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or relieved by <hi>the thin Sophiſtry, of on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a colluſive ambiguity in the word [Lawful,]</hi> which you muſt have recourſe to. For ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you take it in the antecedent ſtrictly, and in the conſequent analogically, in the former, for the <hi>declared pleaſure of a ruler to his Subject;</hi> in the latter, for <hi>an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual fixed principle and rule of acting after one ſteady tenour,</hi> (which are both your own diſtinctions and explications of the word Law), <hi>Let. p.</hi> 41. yet the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is utterly falſe, becauſe depending upon this falſe ground; that whatever man may not do in regard of Gods Law, God himſelf may not do, becauſe of his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or habitual fixed Principle and Rule of acting after one ſteady nature, (as you ſomething odly deſcribe it). In this ſenſe the ſubtil <hi>Twiſſe</hi> rejects <hi>Zuinglius</hi> maxim, <hi>Quod nobis eſt Lex, Deo eſt ingenium &amp;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101372:40"/>is Gods nature to himſelf.</hi> Though in another ſenſe he admits it, That ſuch obligation, as the divine Law lays upon us to do nothing repugnant to it, that Gods nature lays upon him to do nothing repugnant to it. Now then, though it be unlawful to man to kill in ſuch caſes as the Law exempts, yet it is not contrary to Gods nature to kill, and ſo not unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To the <hi>Enthymeme,</hi> we deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, that becauſe in [or from] God is mans help, that therefore it is unlawful for him to deſtroy, for how then does God own himſelf the author of all evils of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6, <hi>Shall there be evil in a City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> And beſides, we ſee not, ſuch is the dimneſs of our ſight, how the conſequence would be proved thereby, were the connexion granted.</p>
               <p>The proofs ſubjoined hang together ſo looſly, that I cannot make ſenſe of them, and therefore will diſmiſs them.</p>
               <p>Your general drift I am aware of, that you deny Predeſtination to evil actions, though you concede it to good, <hi>becauſe it ſeems more congruous to the divine goodneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur</hi> (a term that you will ſtill uſe, though improper enough, to ſignifie that divine action, we call Predetermination, as hath been ſhewn once and again) <hi>to actions that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101372:40"/>have good in them, rather than to theſe that have evil in them, becauſe the one tends to the ſalvation, the other to the deſtruction of man.</hi> To which I anſwer: This Argument, if it hath any weight will bear as hard upon <hi>immediate concurrence,</hi> which you grant to all actions, and ſo to ſinful, as upon Predetermination; and whatever anſwer will relieve you, will with the ſame hand eaſe us. I will pauſe a little with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders leave, and try my skill what anſwer I can excogitate for Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> which will not be a common friend to us both, (as we have been hitherto one to another, and I hope ſhall remain notwithſtanding this publick conteſt): I have thought out my thoughts, and they afford me but three Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That immediate concurrence, as to ſinful actions, divides between the action and the ſinfulneſs; ſo that 'tis only the action as ſuch, which is Gods and mans at once: the ſinfulneſs of it is to be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to man only. And this diſtinction is an open friend to us, and to which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon all fit occaſions we pay our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That if it be granted divine concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is as immediate to evil, as to good actions, (ſo as hath been explained); yet that does not neceſſitate or compel the will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101372:41"/>to any elicite act, [<hi>i. e.</hi> inward acts of willing or nilling]: neither does Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination judg it ſelf guilty, as to any ſuch crime; for that does but put the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon that action, which is produced by Gods immediate concurrence with it. And but that it waits a fitter time to ſpeak out her mind, ſhe could ſay, That ſhe conceives not how ſhe can compel the will to any act, without compelling God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: ſeeing one and the ſame act thereof, is as truly Gods as the creatures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If immediate concurrence thinks her ſelf diſobliged to ſatisfie an inquiſitive cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, as to the <hi>modus</hi> or manner how ſhe joines with the creature in an action, to which ſin does neceſſarily adhere, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing it ſelf is plain, that ſo ſtrict is the dependance of the creature upon the Creator, that it cannot act without Gods immediate concurrence: Predetermination claims the ſame priviledg upon the like ground, that the creature cannot exert its natural powers, till they be applied to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor determine it ſelf to action, till it be determined; which determination can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not include a compulſion of the will, (which is the main, if not the only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie), for if the will act ſpontaneouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from precedent deliberation, how is it forced? if it do not, how is it a will, <hi>i. e.</hi> a rational appetite?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63-123" type="pages">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:101372:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. (which is Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s ſecond), is, <hi>There is no action ſo ſinful, that it hath not ſome natural good as the ſubſtrate of it,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To which Argument, propoſed by way of Queſtion, Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> anſwers, <hi>True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> But then, if that be true, your former poſition, that <hi>ſome actions are evil in the ſubſtance of them,</hi> p. 33. muſt needs be falſe. Let us but formalize the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thus: <hi>ſome actions are ſo ſinful that they have no natural good, as the ſubſtrate matter of them;</hi> [which is the ſenſe of the words juſt now quoted] <hi>no actions are ſo ſinful that they have not ſome natural good, as the ſubſtrate matter of them;</hi> and it will appear, that they are propoſitions contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, and conſequently, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not both be true. They are two known Rules in Logick, <hi>contradictio eſt oppoſitio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter univerſalem &amp; particularem Enunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem [aut propoſitionem]</hi> And, <hi>Harum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terutra ſemper vera, &amp; altera ſemper falſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> preſently flinches, and Sophiſter-like, puts more into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, than was in the premiſes. And <hi>what muſt be inferr'd</hi> (ſays he) <hi>viz.</hi> from his own conceſſion, <hi>That therefore God muſt by a determinative influence produce every ſuch action [what-ever reaſon there be againſt it].</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:101372:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Thoſe words included in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miquadrates are injuriouſly foiſted in. For Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s Argument entirely is thus, <hi>If there be no action ſo ſinful, that it hath not ſome natural good as the ſubſtrate of it, then God is the cauſe,</hi> (viz. by Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>of that natural good that is in every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſed verum prius; Ergo &amp; Poſterius.</hi> And indeed the Argument it ſelf excludes any ſuch addition. For there can be no reaſon againſt Gods production of what is good in any action, unleſs it be (what Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> objects) the accidental adherence of evil thereunto; which, if it be of any moment, militates as much againſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate concurrence, (as hath been ſhown but now). That paſſage of <hi>Auſtins,</hi> oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely offers its ſervice to us, as to the force of Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s Argument, <hi>Deus boni tantummodo cauſa eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e. God is only the cauſe of good, therefore he is not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of evil; becauſe he is the Author of all things that are, which are ſo far good as they are.</hi> 'Tis indeed Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s Argument in other terms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> pretends, Mr. <hi>Gale</hi> might better argue from his premiſes, <hi>The neceſſity of his producing every hour a new world; in which, there would be a great deal more of poſitive entity and natural goodneſs,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 36.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:101372:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This is too great a ſcorn to be caſt upon ſo learned a man, as Mr. <hi>Gale</hi> is well known to be. For there is no <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> that can, with the leaſt probability, be judged likely to be able to tack Mr. <hi>Gales</hi> Antecedent, and Mr. <hi>Howes</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent together. To be ſure, not that which he ſuggeſts; for that is falſe and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a Philoſopher, at leaſt if theſe max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes be true, <hi>ſubſtantia non recipit magis &amp; minus; ens &amp; bonum convertibile;</hi> though 'tis eaſie to conceive there would be more poſitive Beings in number, upon Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s ſuppoſition, yet 'tis hard to conceive there would be a great deal more of poſitive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and ſo of natural goodneſs in the new world, than is already in the old one.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 4. <hi>The natural goodneſs that is in the Entity of an action, is no ſuch invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Holy God, by determinative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to produce it, as that he ſhould offer violence to his own nature, and ſtain the juſtice and honour of his government, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to be done, and then puniſh it, being done,</hi> p. 36.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. The natural goodneſs of an action, hath invitation enough in it to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce God to produce it, both becauſe it is good, and becauſe it cannot be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:101372:43"/>
               <p n="2">2. By Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s own conceſſion, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other does induce God to produce it, by giving and conſerving the powers, and immediate concurrence to the act of thoſe powers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It remains upon Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> to prove, that the producing of an action by deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative influence, is more liable to thoſe abſurdities he names, than the producing it any other way, (except what <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> pitches upon; which if he will alſo own, then I know what I have to rejoyn). In the interim, I am aſhamed he ſhould clog his Reader with, <hi>crambe bis cocta, coleworts twice ſod;</hi> I mean, an odious conſequence impoſed upon <hi>predeterminative influence,</hi> that <hi>it offers violence to Gods nature, and ſtains the juſtice and honour of his Government;</hi> which we ſhall deny, till he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that by it God makes an action to be done, <hi>i. e.</hi> in his ſenſe neceſſitates it to be done, and then puniſhes it being done; which laſt clauſe is very abſurd in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, for it ſuppoſes a contradiction, <hi>viz.</hi> that the action is naturally good, and yet, that God puniſhes the natural goodneſs in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. (which is Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s third and laſt). <hi>The denial of Predetermination, even of ſinful actions as ſuch, cuts off the moſt illuſtrious part of divine providence in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101372:43"/>governing the lower world,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 33.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>I am aſhamed to anſwer it. Name any act of providence, I hereby deny, if you can,</hi> ibid. So Mr. <hi>Howe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. This act of providence thereby you deny, which in words you own, to <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> and <hi>moderate ſinful actions,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 45. This will appear by conſidering what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence your mediate or immediate concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (for you do ſo fluctuate, that I know not which of the two you will abide by), can have upon this effect. <hi>The mediate</hi> can have none, for that is nothing elſe but a conſervation of the being, with its powers and faculties, and ſo but abuſively called <hi>concurrence</hi> or <hi>concourſe;</hi> and ſo does but keep the powers indeterminate, not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, nor limit their acts: nor yet can <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> limit any action, becauſe as ſuch, it is neither before nor after the creatures action, but with it. The withdrawing of concourſe immediate, may hinder, I grant, the creatures action: but whether God does ever withdraw it or no, <hi>Strangius.</hi> L. 1. c. 11. p. 65. doubts, and ſo may you, perhaps, upon his ground. Let us, for the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification of this limitation, conſider it, with reſpect to thoſe things which it is converſant about.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>objects of its acts;</hi> as, that <hi>Abſaloms</hi> Adultery with <hi>Davids</hi> wifes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101372:44"/>than any other women. This is plain, by comparing 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.22. In the former place, the words are, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, I will raiſe up evil againſt thee out of thine own houſe: and I will take thy wives before thine eyes, and give them unto thy neighbour; and he ſhall lye with thy wives in the ſight of the Sun.</hi> In the latter place the event anſwers the threat. <hi>And Abſalom went in unto his Fathers Concubines in the ſight of all Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As <hi>to the time, when,</hi> or <hi>how long</hi> the ſinful acts ſhall be exerciſed about their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>When,</hi> Gen. 45.5, <hi>God did ſend me before you to preſerve life,</hi> ſays <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his Brethren; whereas, they might not have ſold him, till the famine came. <hi>How long;</hi> That is intimated in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3, <hi>The rod of the wicked ſhall not rest upon the lot of the Righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As <hi>to the event,</hi> or iſſue of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That an oppreſſour ſhall impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, not utterly undo him he does op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs: that he who ſtrikes his neighbour with an intent to kill him, ſhall yet but wound him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>As to the decree of the act,</hi> Pſal. 76.10, <hi>Surely the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee; the remainder of wrath thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>cinges, ligabis;</hi> which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101372:44"/>of binding up the faculty, that it put not forth its utmoſt force in the act iſſuing from it: as when a man is but in a pet, as we ſay, not outragiouſly angry. Thus God makes as great a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſame man and himſelf, as a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der does when he uſes a ſtrait rein, or lays the bridle on his Horſes neck.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The over-ruling and diſpoſing of a ſinful action to good, againſt the deſign and inclination of the ſinful Agent, <hi>Poſtſc.</hi> p. 45. n. 10. is an act of Providence, which Mr <hi>Howe</hi> denies, in the denial of Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination. For <hi>immediate concurrence</hi> is all that Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> allows of; which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but Gods action with the creature, and not exiſtent before nor after it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore direct the action to any end. And particularly in puniſhing one ſin with another. As in the inſtance of <hi>Abſalom;</hi> his Adultery with his Fathers Concubines, was a puniſhment of <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s Wife. In this and ſuch like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, God is the Author, <hi>ordinis in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> though not <hi>mali,</hi> as the moſt learned Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> Dean of of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> expreſſes it, of the Church, p. 131, 132). <hi>i. e. God is the Author of the order of conſequence, that one evil ſhall follow another, and have the reaſon of a puniſhment thereof;</hi> which how he can be, is no way explicable, but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101372:45"/>by the Doctrine of <hi>Predetermination</hi> which, importing an application of the crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to action, and to one rather than an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other, and at one time rather than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as hath been ſhown) gives an eaſie account, how God may diſpoſe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions to good ends, and particularly to this, to be puniſhments of preceding ſins.</p>
               <p>And now, it is high time that we take a view of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s Arguments, for the negative of the Queſtion hitherto diſcuſſed, for which we muſt return to his Letter again, where he ſtates the <hi>Theſis</hi> he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, as importing <hi>an irreſiſtble predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative concurrence to all actions of the creature, even to thoſe that are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt malignantly wicked,</hi> Let. p. 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Here are divers ambiguities in the terms (beſides that of predeterminative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, which hath been faulted already, as not very proper).</p>
               <p n="1">1. The term <hi>irreſiſtible;</hi> which may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther import, <hi>a neceſſity of infallibility,</hi> as to the event, or a <hi>neceſſity of coaction</hi> or compulſion. If he takes it in the former ſenſe, 'tis altogether improperly. For ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible, imports a relation of the action of the agent, to ſome reſiſtance or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraction of the patient; as when the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter endeavours to put out the fire, which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101372:45"/>would lick it up; or in free agents, when a man with all his ſtrength reſiſts him that by force would carry him away Priſoner. If he underſtands the term in the latter and proper ſenſe, I underſtand not why he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the term upon our Theſis; for we do not aſſert any compulſion in Predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the will, nor can we conceive it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in any caſe; not if we ſhould ſuppoſe <hi>per impoſsibile,</hi> a rational creature made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no Law at all; for then as it would have a power, and alſo an inclination to uſe it, ſo there would be no need of any force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to act; not ſuppoſing it (as it is) under a Law, would there be any need of compulſion, not as to good actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are gracious habits to diſpoſe the will to actions congenerous; not as to evil actions, (no not if God did predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to them as ſuch) for the will in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſinful habits is of it ſelf inclined enough to any evil actions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>term,</hi> in themſelves moſt malignant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked. To which I ſay, that it may be underſtood in a double ſenſe, either with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, <hi>to the different kind of Laws</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit actions, thus; Thoſe actions are ſaid to be in themſelves evil which are a breach of the <hi>Law of nature,</hi> and ſo are oppoſed to thoſe which are evil only by a <hi>poſitive law;</hi> or elſe with reference <hi>to the degrees of recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101372:46"/>in one and the ſame Law;</hi> thus ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are ſaid to be in themſelves evil, when they are evil in regard of their object, as that is oppoſed to the end and circumſtances. Thus the hatred of God, and Adultery, are in themſelves evil, becauſe no end or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance can make them good; but giving Alms out of vain glory is not in it ſelf evil, becauſe changing the end, the action is good, that before was bad.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> underſtands the term in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, and overlooks the genuine ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it; <hi>viz.</hi> thus, that <hi>wickedneſs is of the eſſence of ſome actions.</hi> This I collect from that clauſe, <hi>Nothing is more apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſimple and moſt ſtrictly natural impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, than to ſeparate the malignity thereof from an intrinſecally evil action,</hi> Let. p. 33. Now 'tis plain enough, if we take <hi>the hatred of God,</hi> which is Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s inſtance of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it ſelf evil, that the evil of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is ſeparable from it, for the ſame paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if the Devil be the object of it, is good. And the evil of this action is as ſeparable from it, as in actions that are evil, as to their circumſtances. As to read the Scriptures, when it is our preſent duty to hearken to the Sermon. The reaſon is the ſame in both, the action of hatred is evil only in regard of the undue object, and the action of reading the Scriptures only in regard of the undue cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101372:46"/>of time. And if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands <hi>actions in themſelves evil, of actions eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially evil,</hi> let him enjoy his own ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but let him not impoſe it upon us, who look upon it as one of the greateſt abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties a learned man can be guilty of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. To ſtate the Queſtion therefore aright (though we have done it before) we ſay, that we reject the term <hi>irreſiſtible,</hi> as not being in the Queſtion, but being a begging of the Queſtion, becauſe it ſuppoſes ſome force on Gods part the Agent, which the Creature as far as it can reſiſts. And we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own the <hi>diſtinction of actions,</hi> which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> introduces into the Queſtion, for we know of none that are <hi>in themſelves malignantly wicked;</hi> that is (in his ſenſe) <hi>eſſentially evil.</hi> But that which we aſſert is, That God does predetermine the Creature as well to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are evil, as to thoſe that are good. Let us now hear his Arguments againſt our Aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Arg. 1. <hi>If there be an irreſiſtible deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative concurrence to all, and ſo to wicked actions of the Creature, then the matter of all Gods Laws in reference to all wicked actions was a ſimple and moſt ſtrictly natural im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility.</hi> But the Antecedent is, Therefore we muſt own the conſequent, <hi>Let. p.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. In general, If we take his words ſimply as they found, we ſee not but we may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:101372:47"/>grant the whole, with as little inconvenience to our aſſertion as to his. For the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will be the ſame, if ſome of his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be placed for an Antecedent in the room of ours. If God does certainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know all, and ſo all wicked actions of the Creature, then for the Creature not to do thoſe wicked actions, was <hi>a ſimple and moſt ſtrictly natural impoſſibility.</hi> For 'tis as truly impoſſible that ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts ſhould not be ſuch as God fore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ows they will be; as that men ſhould yield obedience to the Laws of God, when God hinders them <hi>thorugh his own irreſiſtible counteraction,</hi> Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s phraſe <hi>p.</hi> 37. Again, we may argue thus, If there be an irreſiſtible determinative concurrence to all good actions of the Creature, then the matter of all Gods Laws in reference to all good actions was <hi>a ſimple and moſt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly natural impoſſibility; i.e.</hi> it is ſimply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that good men ſhould not do thoſe good actions, exacted of them by the Law. As to this laſt, I cannot apprehend any reaſon why Predeterminative concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to evil actions ſhould make the avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them impoſſible; and the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence to good actions ſhould leave the neglect of them poſſible.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But becauſe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> intends more by <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> than the Predeterminants can allow him, we ſhall borrow a little learning
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101372:47"/>from the Schools for the explication of it. It is a Queſtion in Metaphyſicks, <hi>An poſſibile &amp; contingens a parte rei aequipolleant;</hi> i.e. <hi>Whether for a thing to be poſſible and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the ſame ſignification or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> To which it is anſwered affirmative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Si poſſibile accipiatur pro eo quod ſeſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet indifferenter ut ſit;</hi> i. e. <hi>If for a thing to be poſsible be taken for an indifferency to be or not to be.</hi> And by the like reaſon <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> muſt be terms equipol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, if <hi>impoſsible</hi> be taken <hi>for that which is not indifferent to be, and not to be; or, which as it is not, ſo nor can it be.</hi> 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that Impoſſible is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontrary to Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; as Neceſſary is taken generally for that which cannot but be, and Impoſſible for that which cannot be: yet theſe two are equipollent, if the one be affirmed, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther denied; for that which is neceſſary to be, is impoſſible not to be; and that which is neceſſary not to be, is impoſſible to be; and on the other hand, That which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be, is neceſſary not to be; and that which is impoſſible not to be, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be. We muſt therefore make a little enquiry into the kinds of <hi>neceſsity,</hi> which as to things is either <hi>ſimple,</hi> or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</hi> The latter (for the former is irrela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to our buſineſs) agrees to things in their coheſion or connexion each with other; this
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101372:48"/>is divided into a <hi>neceſsity of the conſequent,</hi> and of <hi>conſequence,</hi> or <hi>abſolute,</hi> and <hi>reſpective.</hi> The former is a connexion of thoſe things which cannot be ſever'd without a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; <hi>i.e.</hi> deſtroying the nature of their ſubject. So juſtice to God, reaſon to man, agree ſo neceſſarily to their ſubjects, that if you deny either, you do in effect deny them to be what they are, The latter, a neceſſity whereby thoſe things that are not in their own nature conjoined, are yet upon ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomething antecedent conjoined for this or that time. Whence <hi>Baronius</hi> calls the former, <hi>a neceſsity of nature;</hi> the latter, <hi>an accidental neceſsity.</hi> Of this latter ſort is this example, If Iſlanders will export Goods out of their own Country, they muſt make uſe of Ships. And from theſe modes of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it is eaſie to collect the modes of Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, That ſomething is, ſaid to be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, either <hi>abſolutely,</hi> which involves a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, as for a ſtone to be a man; or <hi>reſpectively,</hi> as if a man will fly that he ſhould have wings. And here we may ſtop a while and obſerve how Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath <hi>gratified his own unſcholaſtick humour,</hi> in neglecting the ſtrictneſs of Scholaſtick terms, to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of his own aſſertion. For I am much miſtaken if it is not plain enough that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> confounds the diſtinction of <hi>neceſsity</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibility,</hi> into <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>reſpective;</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101372:48"/>makes the matter of Gods Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon ſuppoſition of Gods irreſiſtible determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to wicked actions, to be an <hi>impoſsibility</hi> of both kinds, and ſo of neither. For if it be an impoſſibility only upon Hypotheſis of Determinative influence, how is it a <hi>ſimple and ſtrictly natural impoſsibility?</hi> If it be a <hi>ſimple,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>impoſsibility,</hi> how is it an impoſſibility only upon an Hypotheſis? [<hi>viz.</hi> that now mentioned.]</p>
               <p>Way being thus made by explication of the Terms, to the antecedent or minor, I anſwer by denial, That the Determinative Influence to all wicked actions we aſſert, does infer any coaction on the Will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> If Determination of the Will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports Coaction, or is inconſiſtent with the freedom of the Will; then it is either from ſome general reaſon agreeing to all Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or from ſome ſpecial reaſon agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only to this Determination, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions; but neither of theſe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it does not import any ſuch thing at all; no Determination of the Will in general does import Coaction, or deſtroy its liberty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Upon Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s own conceſſion of a <hi>Predetermination of good actions,</hi> Poſt. p. 39. which I preſume he will not aſſirm to be <hi>compulſory;</hi> yet becauſe I cannot ſee a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he ſhould not, (as well as of evil actions) I will ſuppoſe him to acknowledg
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101372:49"/>it. And then I would demand whether God compels men to the natural actions as ſuch, or to them as morally good. Not to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral actions as ſuch, but to them there is no need of it, <hi>for the powers that produce them, are apt and habile for any congenerous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s confeſſion, <hi>Poſt. p.</hi> 45. Not to the actions as good, for the powers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing renewed by Grace, (ſo far as they are ſuch) need but an excitation, not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It appears from the general principle of Divines, <hi>Libertas a coactione eſt eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis voluntatis proprietas;</hi> i. e. <hi>That liberty from force and compulſion is an eſſential pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the will.</hi> Which may be thus evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. 1. By the nature of the wills liberty, that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſpontaneum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuale;</hi> i.e. <hi>ſpontaneum praeeunte intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus lumine vel judicio,</hi> as <hi>Strang.</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, <hi>De Vol. Dei, p.</hi> 686. That is, <hi>an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual ſpontaneity.</hi> A <hi>ſpontaneity</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the acting of neceſſary agents, ſuch as the Sun in ſhining; and <hi>Intellectual,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it from that ſpontaneity which agrees to brutes, or to mankind, who are acted by fancy, without previous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Infants, Fools, Mad-men, who whileſt they remain ſuch, are brutes in the ſhape of men and women.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It appears by the repugnancy of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:101372:49"/>terms in conjunction. For the Will to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced is but <hi>invita aliquid velle,</hi> i. e. <hi>to will any thing unwillingly;</hi> which were to will and not will the ſame object at the ſame time, which is an implicit contradiction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis not from any peculiar reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to ſinful actions. If there be any, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would befriend the world to bring it to light. Which will appear,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Upon Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s grounds, if Coaction be inſeparable from compulſion, upon any ſpecial reaſon agreeing to one ſort of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rather than another, it muſt be with reſpect to good actions, not to evil. For God determines the Will by <hi>irreſiſtible grace,</hi> to ſuch actions as by nature ſince the fall it is averſe unto; and remains ſo in a degree after the bleſſed change it hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone: whereas the Will having a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bias to evil, [as it is not, ſo nor] does it need to be predetermined, <hi>i.e.</hi> forced, [if Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> be a faithful interpreter of the word.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are manifeſt indications of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in ſinful actions, pregnant proofs that man hath not only <hi>potentiam in ſe liberam,</hi> but <hi>liberum uſum potentiae;</hi> i.e. <hi>a power in it ſelf free, but as to them a free uſe of his power.</hi> An inſtance of his own, <hi>hatred of God,</hi> will ſerve our turn. This act muſt be <hi>ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous,</hi> or 'tis not the act of an humane will,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101372:50"/>which is an [intellectual] <hi>appetite;</hi> no, nor of a ſenſitive appetite, for to this laſt ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneity is eſſential, and <hi>intellectual</hi> too: and ſo it is, for it proceeds from, and is guided by a precedent [though miſtaken] judgment of the underſtanding, which repreſents God to him as a Tyrant, that abuſes his authority by needleſs reſtraints upon mans natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations. Suppoſe to unchaſtity with any woman whoſe skin and features attract his liking. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethrens hatred of him, was determined by God to the ſelling, rather than killing of him; yet as they acted ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly, ſo upon precedent conſideration. Two Reaſons determined their choice of the milder courſe of the two they had in view, <hi>He is our Brother, and our Fleſh, and what profit is it if we ſlay him, and conceal his blood?</hi> Gen. 37.26.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If there be any reaſon to infer Coaction from Predetermination, it muſt be the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of neceſſity on Gods part, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingency on mans: Which if it be univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then I know not how Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> will ſalve the objection againſt <hi>immediate concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> [which he ſeems to grant,] <hi>that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the liberty of the will ſeems to be loſt, both as to the exerciſe and ſpecification of the act.</hi> Unleſs as <hi>Burgeſdicius</hi> does, (whoſe ſolution offers it ſervice, he being the firſt Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101372:50"/>Author that ever I read,) <hi>That the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of God takes not away the contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of voluntary actions, becauſe it does not precede the action of the ſecond cauſe.</hi> Burg. Met. l. 2. c. 11. n. 9. But then that reaſon (if aſſented to) will give a mortal wound to the Predeſtination (which certainly precedes them) of good actions, which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges: or if he will looſe the knot artificially, he muſt ſay that the concourſe of God is ſo accommodated to the nature and manner of the creatures acting, that notwithſtanding it, natural cauſes act neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, and voluntary cauſes contingently, or freely; and then the ſame anſwer will fit Predetermination of free agents to all their actions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The denial of the conſiſtency between liberty and neceſſity in general, will bear as hard upon (what we grant, and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> cannot deny) <hi>actions in themſelves good,</hi> as <hi>Amor Dei,</hi> the love of God; as it can do upon (what we deny, and you aſſert) <hi>actions in themſelves evil,</hi> as <hi>odium Dei,</hi> the hatred of God. And harder, for the Will is but in part free to good actions, when as 'tis wholly free, I mean diſpoſed and inclined to evil actions. We are now the better prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by way thus made, to anſwer Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s proofs of his conſequence. Which are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Not to do an action whereto the agent
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101372:51"/>is determined by an infinite power is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> Let. p. 33. <hi>Ergo,</hi> not to do wicked acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, [for that's the ſum of his conſequent, in his Hyp. Syll. whereof this Enthymeme is a proof] to which the creature is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined is impoſsible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. In general, that [ſuppoſing his Antecedent true, as 'tis in the ſenſe before given] yet the impoſsibility he ſpeaks of is not <hi>a ſimple and moſt ſtrictly natural impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility,</hi> which he before aſſerted; but an <hi>impoſſibility reſpective,</hi> to the determination of an infinite power, (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 2. That if he intends a <hi>reſpective or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional impoſſibility,</hi> I grant his Enthymeme, for it hurts our Hypotheſis no more than his, viz. <hi>of determination to good actions.</hi> For all determination does infer a neceſsity, that the thing determined ſhould be, as it is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be; or an impoſsibility, that the thing determined ſhould not be, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 3. If we muſt ſupply from the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poth. major, the term <hi>irreſiſtibly</hi> to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie the <hi>determination</hi> he oppoſes, and we muſt underſtand by it <hi>compulſion</hi> or <hi>force,</hi> we again concede the whole without any diſadvantage to us. And ſo we may rid our hands of it, as an ignoble begging of the Queſtion, for that was incumbent on
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:101372:51"/>him to prove, not to take for granted, that our Predetermination imports a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s ſecond Enthymeme is this, <hi>To ſeparate the malignity of an action intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally evil is impoſsible,</hi> p. 33. <hi>Ergo,</hi> not to do ſuch wicked actions to which the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is determined, is impoſsible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. Granting his Antecedent for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments ſake, I cannot imagine how he will defend the <hi>immediate concurrence of God to all the actions of his creatures;</hi> and ſo to ſinful actions, and ſo to thoſe (if there be any ſuch) as are in themſelves evil, againſt the charge of involving God in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of ſinful actions, as ſuch, ſeeing by Divine immediate concurrence the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecally evil action is as much Gods as mans action. <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Strangius</hi> (who are as Heterodox as Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) do both confeſs, that <hi>it is very hard to ſhew how God may be freed from that charge, when-as he co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates with the creature to every ſinful action. Bar. Met.</hi> 98. <hi>D.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 72. <hi>Strang. de Vol. Dei. p.</hi> 344, 372. Though Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would lay the <hi>great difficulty and encumbrance infer'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Religion,</hi> only upon <hi>Predetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive concourſe to wicked actions.</hi> Yet, the Learned <hi>Ameſius,</hi> a Predeterminant, tells us not without reaſon, <hi>Deformitas moralis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis annexa videtur actui in exercito, quam
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101372:52"/>in applicatione ad agendum.</hi> Cont. Grev. p. 189. i.e. <hi>Moral deformity ſeems more cloſely joined to action, than to application unto action.</hi> For an object may be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently preſented to the eye, which may put a man upon action, <hi>viz.</hi> unchaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 2. We will grant the Antecedent, <hi>ex animo,</hi> becauſe it does implicate, that there ſhould be any ſuch action. 'Tis a received maxim, <hi>Malum eſt in bono, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in ſubjecto,</hi> i.e. <hi>Evil is in good, as in its ſubject.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s ſaying is well known, and as well approved, <hi>Ipſum quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulum-cunque eſſe bonum eſt, quia ſummum eſſe bonum eſt.</hi> De vera Rel. c. 34. i.e. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf how inconſiderable ſoever is good, becauſe the chiefeſt Being is good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 3. We deny that there cannot be a ſeparation of an action, from the evil of it. Of this ſeparation there are many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: ſuppoſing Uſury lawful, (which I will not now diſpute) I may lawfully take up money at uſe at Ten pounds <hi>per Cent.</hi> (if my neceſsity require it) when the Intereſt allowed by Law (which to break in matters of publick benefit is ſinful) is but 6 <hi>l.</hi> A Chriſtian Prince may urge the great <hi>Turk</hi> to ſwear to Articles of Peace, though the former knows the latter will ſwear by his <hi>Mahomet.</hi> Theſe are inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101372:52"/>of <hi>our concurrence to the actions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a remoter kind,</hi> [than God does concur to the actions of his creature] as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe, <hi>Poſt. p.</hi> 33. And by the like reaſon may God <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatively concur</hi> (as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> delights to ſpeak, though not accurately) to an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is evil, and yet not to the evil of it; which the Learned <hi>Twiſſe</hi> illuſtrates by divers pretty ſimilitudes. <hi>An Horſeman that puts on a lame horſe to go, is the cauſe of his motion, not of his halting, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from ſome hurt in his leg, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of motion. The Sun by his warmth makes the dunghill ſtink, of which ſtink that that warmth is not the cauſe appears, in that the very ſame influence draws forth a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſavour from a bed of Roſes. That the dunghill ſmells is from the Suns drawing forth the vapour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, but that it ſmells ill is from the condition of the matter. The up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-wheel of a Clock, though by its motion it draws along with it an under-wheel, that is irregular in its motion, yet it is not the cauſe of that irregularity. When a dexterous Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man writes upon ſinking paper he makes</hi> [pothooks, as we ſay of children that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to learn the art of writing] <hi>blots ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than letters, which yet is not his fault, but the Papers.</hi> Twiſſe Vind. Gr. l. 2. p. 1 <hi>a.</hi> p. 26.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:101372:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 4. There muſt needs be a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion [and therefore 'tis poſſible to be] between actions, and the evil of them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s own Hypotheſis <hi>(viz.) That God does predetermine to all good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which in the preſent ſtate are but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly good. Here he muſt diſtinguiſh between the efficiency of God and man, as to the ſame action, and aſcribe the action and grace of it to God, and the evil that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to that action to man, unleſs he will aſcribe all to God. <hi>Abſit blaſphemia verbo!</hi> If Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> can extricate himſelf, and not us with the ſame Anſwer; or rather, if he can excogitate any other Anſwer, than by this exſibilated diſtinction—<hi>erit mihi magnus Apollo,</hi> and without an Irony, <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientum octavus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 2. To the <hi>connexion.</hi> I Anſwer, That it infolds a twofold contradiction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For it ſuppoſes ſome actions to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally evil,</hi> and yet (by our Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis), to be <hi>determined,</hi> i. e. <hi>compell'd,</hi> (if Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> may be admitted our Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter); whereas, that is not ſin which is not <hi>ſpontaneous,</hi> neither is that <hi>ſpontaneous</hi> which is <hi>neceſſary,</hi> i. e. <hi>violent</hi> [or compell'd]. For <hi>violence is a Phyſical action upon the Patient; in which ſort of actions vertue or vice hath no place: for the will is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of moral actions.</hi> So the learned <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:101372:53"/>de <hi>Scand.</hi> p. 98. [where note, that I preſume <hi>Camero</hi> denies not original ſin im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, to be <hi>ſuo modo,</hi> i. e. <hi>in its kind vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,</hi> [and ſo truly ſin], according to St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> ſentiments, <hi>nos omnes eramus ille unus homo,</hi> i.e. <hi>we were all that one man, [Adam],</hi> and ſo ſinned in him. This to prevent any miſapprehenſion].</p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſuppoſes ſin to have an efficient cauſe, whereas 'tis a known Rule in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, <hi>Peccatum qua tale &amp; eſſentialiter eſt effectus moralis, &amp; non habet cauſam Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,</hi> i. e. <hi>Sin as ſuch, and eſſentially is a moral effect, and hath no Phyſical cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 3. Having given an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Howe's Antecedent,</hi> and <hi>Connexion,</hi> we ſhall now proceed to raze the foundation of his Hypotheſis, by proving, that there are no actions of free agents evil in themſelves; or that no moral evil is poſitive, but only privative, (which latter are the common terms of Philoſophers and Divines, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into the nature of moral evil). And I ſhall borrow one Argument, which will be inſtead of all, from the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Barlow,</hi> the now Renowned Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. <hi>Every real and poſitive Being is from God the author and firſt cauſe of all Being. But moral evil [formally] taken, is not from God the author and firſt cauſe of all Being.</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:101372:54"/>Ergo, <hi>moral evil [formally taken] is not a real and poſitive Being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor is evident, and acknowledged by the very Heathens, in the appellation of</hi> Optimus, <hi>the Beſt, which they apply to their</hi> Jupiter, <hi>together with</hi> Maximus <hi>the Greateſt:</hi> [And will no doubt be owned by Mr. <hi>Howe;</hi> who, <hi>eo nomine,</hi> for that very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, rejects Predeſtination of evil actions, becauſe, in his apprehenſion, it makes God the author of moral evil].</p>
               <p>The <hi>Major,</hi> let us hear the learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop prove, [and the rather, becauſe it will much confirm our firſt Argument for Predetermination of all actions as ſuch].</p>
               <p>Proof. <hi>Becauſe it is impoſſible that there ſhould be any finite and created Being, which does not depend, and hath its Being from an infinite and uncreated Being, [viz.</hi> God]; <hi>for it muſt needs be, if there be any Being not cauſed by God, that that Being be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent upon God as the firſt cauſe; and conſequently, God ſhall not be the firſt cauſe in reſpect of that Being, whence follow many abſurdities,</hi> &amp;c. [whereof I ſhall only take the ſum, as himſelf hath given it us, with an application to moral evil]. <hi>If moral evil,</hi> [i.e. <hi>any ſin or breach of Divine Law], be a real Being; then,</hi> 1. <hi>God ſhall not be the cauſe of that Being; for of ſo deformed a birth, divine goodneſs cannot be the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:101372:54"/>2. <hi>This granted, it will follow,</hi> 1. <hi>That there is a ſecondary Being, and a Being by participation, [ſuch as every finite Being is ſuppoſed to be]; which does not partake of [or receive its] being from the firſt Being.</hi> 2. <hi>That there is a finite Being independent upon God, both as to production and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. All which things we know, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are contrary, not only to Philoſophy, but Divinity.</hi> Thus far the moſt acute Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher and Divine, <hi>Exercit. metaph.</hi> 2 <hi>a. de natura mali, ad calcem Scheib. met.</hi> p. 32, 33.</p>
               <p>Let us take notice of the inſtances of thoſe ſins, which are ſuppoſed to be evil in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, [or poſitive].</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. Sins of commiſſion which are evil, <hi>ex genere &amp; objecto;</hi> (whereof two are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially inſiſted on: <hi>Adams eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit,</hi> and [by Mr. <hi>Howe] the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of God)</hi> are in themſelves evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In general. <hi>If all ſins ſubſiſt in ſome actual motion of the ſoul, body, or both, and this motion abſtractively conſidered, be the material part of every actual ſin, and hath God for the prime cauſe, in whom we live, and move, and have our being; then no ſin can be aſſigned, wherein this material part may not be found.</hi> So the Learned <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Sariſbury, Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madv.</hi> on <hi>Hoard,</hi> p. 174, 175.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:101372:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. As to the inſtances. The firſt, <hi>in eating the forbidden fruit, the material part of the ſin, in regard of the Soul was the appetition thereof; in regard of the body, the maſtication [chewing] and manducation [eating], and other bodily acts. Separate theſe from the formal part, which is</hi> modus appetendi, <hi>the manner of deſiring, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a repugnancy to Gods command, and God was the prime author thereof. The act of deſiring and eating muſt of neceſſity be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to God, without whom there neither is nor can be any motion of body or ſoul: but the diſorderly manner of deſiring and eating contrary to the Law of God, this is reducible (as being a defect) only to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective will of man,</hi> Davenant. ibid. p. 175. As to the ſecond inſtance, <hi>hatred of God;</hi> That the act terminated upon that object, <hi>in complexo,</hi> is evil, and cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we deny not; but then, that is true of <hi>acts and undue ends,</hi> as Hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty out of vain-glory; of <hi>acts and undue circumſtances,</hi> as walking in the Fields, when we ſhould be at Church; as of <hi>acts and undue objects,</hi> whereof this is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. And ſo all ſinful actions are evil, as to their ſubſtance, which Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> hath not affirmed. That hatred of God is not evil in it ſelf, <hi>becauſe the act invaried, the object but changed, that act which was evil,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:101372:55"/>is become morally good.</hi> So our Learned Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> again, <hi>Exerc. met. p.</hi> 41. which he illuſtrates and proves by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Adultery, where the act being the ſame for the ſubſtance, is altered in its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reſpect, by making the woman, with whom I committed Adultery, my wife,</hi> Id. ibid. Which inſtance of our Learned Biſhop is plain, in the caſe of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> whoſe ſociety together was unlawful before, but lawful after their marriage. They that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire further ſatisfaction in this point, may do well to have recourſe to a learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe in our native Language, of Mr. <hi>H. Hickman, of the poſitivity of ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. One ſin is the cauſe of another, as original ſin inherent [as that ſtands op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to original ſin imputed] is the cauſe of actual ſins; therefore ſin is not meerly privative.</p>
               <p>Sol. <hi>The privation which is in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral propenſion of the will to ſin, [in which natural propenſion original ſin conſiſte], is not the real efficient of evil actions; but the will, in regard of that propenſion, is the real and true cauſe of evil actions.</hi> So <hi>Baron. wet.</hi> §. 5. <hi>n.</hi> 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. Our Divines do make a poſitive part in original ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Yet they hold ſin to be <hi>only Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> But then it will be demanded how
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:101372:56"/>their aſſertions will agree together.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, In inherent ſin there is ſaid to be a poſitive and a negative Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. This latter Divines call a want of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal righteouſneſs, or <hi>not to be able to do good.</hi> The former, they call a pravity of nature, or <hi>to be able to do evil</hi> only, which is called <hi>Poſitive Legice,</hi> becauſe 'tis expreſſed affirmatively; whereas the latter is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed negatively: ſo <hi>Maccov. op.</hi> Poſt. p. 83. [r. <hi>fuſe de hac re diſſerentem</hi> Giſb. Voet. Diſp. Theol. p. 1. p. 1084</p>
               <p>Arg. 2. <hi>If God hath a prede erminative concurrence to the moſt wicked actions, it is then no way explicable how the influence and concurrence the holy God hath to the worſt of actions, is to be diſtinguiſhed from that which he affords to the beſt; wherein ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herently evil actions are leſs to be imputed to him who forbids them, than to the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Tempter, who prompts to them, or to the actor that doth them, or wherein not a great deal more?</hi> Let. p. 32, 33. which Argument Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> gives us more conciſely after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>That God hath as much influence and concurrence to the worſt actions, as to the beſt; as much or more than the ſinner or the Tempter,</hi> Poſtſc. p. 25. [<hi>viz.</hi> according to our Doctrine].</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If our learned Adverſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the <hi>antecedent,</hi> as we do whom
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:101372:56"/>he oppoſes, of the <hi>materiale</hi> of wicked acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we grant his conſequence: for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet ſee the inconvenience of owning, that there is an univerſal or indifferent influence upon the actions of free Agents, as ſuch, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from their morality. The actions of the underſtanding and will <hi>Phyſically</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, are neither holy nor ſinful; thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations being taken from the relation of the actions to the Law preſcribed, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with, or deviation from it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>in linea Phyſica,</hi> Gods influence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence is the ſame, when they are the <hi>ſubſtrate matter of moral evil, and moral good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If he intends the <hi>formale,</hi> or rather, the moſt wicked actions, <hi>in concreto,</hi> we diſown the <hi>antecedent</hi> as none of ours, and complain of his diſingenuity in pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch an aſſertion upon our ſleeve.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet however, for his ſatisfaction, I ſhall let him know, That (beſides the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon good and bad actions in what degree ſoever, which we acknowledg com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both) there are divers differences of the influence we own for diſtinguiſhing of good actions from bad.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That as to good actions God does, <hi>in genere phyſico, re create</hi> thoſe internal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, which he did <hi>concreate</hi> in the ſtate of innocency, with the ſeveral faculties, in which they were reſpectively ſeated, (as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101372:57"/>knowledg in the underſtanding; a rectitude of the will, conſiſting in a compliance with the laſt dictates of the practical underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing); that they might be <hi>[actus primi,</hi> or] principles of [the <hi>actus ſecundi,</hi> or] operations of the faculties, [in vertue of thoſe habits], which [faculties] he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences to reduce them to act, by that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence which we call <hi>Predetermination.</hi> But as to evil actions, God inſuſes no evil, neither indeed can he (beſides the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy ſuch an action would carry to his holineſs); becauſe, though ſin be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conceived by us, <hi>per modum habitus poſitivi,</hi> under the notion of a poſitive ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, yet it is not properly ſo, and ſo is not capable of production by that immediate ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, (which we call <hi>infuſion),</hi> as hath been, in part, demonſtrated before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to good actions God does in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determination to them, ſo excite to the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that withal he adds new ſtrength to the habits given, whence thoſe acts imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately proceed; which he does not neither as to evil actions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We have a third difference from Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s own conceſsion: <hi>The ordinary appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted way for the communication of this determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native influence is by our intervening conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the inducements which God repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to us in his Word,</hi> viz. <hi>The Precepts,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:101372:57"/>Promiſes, and Comminations, which are th. moral inſtruments of his Government.</hi> Poſtſc p. 40. The meaning of which words, is, that God is not only a <hi>Phyſical,</hi> but alſo a <hi>moral cauſe</hi> of good actions: whereas 'tis our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent, that God is only a <hi>Phyſical cauſe</hi> of the actions to which ſin inheres, but not a <hi>moral cauſe</hi> of the ſin adhering to them. And (if I do not too much truſt my own judgment) this obſervation is not contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the evincing of it; that the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency of the will to chuſe or refuſe the Object propoſed by the underſtanding, is not ſo natural to the will, but that it may be inclined by an inherent quality to chuſe or refuſe one object rather than another.</p>
               <p>As for the compariſon which he makes between <hi>God, the ſinner and the Tempter,</hi> (upon our grounds), and gives God the precedency of them both in his influence upon wicked actions, 'tis an <hi>odious and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible calumny,</hi> not backed with any proof; as he intends it of ſuch actions <hi>in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete,</hi> i. e. as including with the action the ſinfulneſs of it too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> To it I reply, That a <hi>ſhort Horſe is ſoon curried.</hi> This ſlight objection is eaſily anſwered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> means <hi>as much phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical influence,</hi> or <hi>moral:</hi> If the former, we ſay <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>ſinner</hi> have both a <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:101372:58"/>influence,</hi> upon the action that is evil, but the <hi>Tempter</hi> none at all; and that, as to the evil of it, their <hi>phyſical influence</hi> is alike, <hi>i. e.</hi> they have none at all; for ſin not being a <hi>phyſical effect,</hi> cannot have a <hi>phyſical cauſe.</hi> If the latter, (beſides that that influence is not in the Queſtion), the <hi>Sinner</hi> and the <hi>Tempter</hi> have influence and concurrence to wicked actions, and <hi>God</hi> not at all: for neither by Commands, Counſels, Threats, nor Promiſes, does he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce men to ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Were it ſo; yet the <hi>immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence,</hi> which he acknowledges <hi>to all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and ſo to ſinful actions; in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the notion he entertains with ſelf-applauſe, <hi>of the inſeparableneſs of the evil of ſome actions from the actions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> makes himſelf obnoxious to the ſame charge of making Gods concurrence with ſinful actions, to be as much or more than the <hi>Sinners,</hi> or the <hi>Tempters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. Laſtly, he charges the Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of ſinful actions with <hi>irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilableneſs with Gods wiſdom and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Poſtſc. p.</hi> 25. by which, &amp;c. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume he intends, <hi>in his Counſels, Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and what-ever means he uſes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them,</hi> (which are the expreſſions he uſes in the Title-Page of his Letter, in reference to Preſcience).</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:101372:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> As to both of theſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, I am not aware of any thing well ſaid by Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> for the reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Gods Preſcience with them, which may not by a juſt proportion be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Gods Predetermination. For the evincing whereof, we will caſt his Diſcourſe into Paragraphs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſpeak particularly of <hi>Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That there ſhould be a direct and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit contradiction between fore-knowing and dehorting, we may at firſt ſight perceive the terms cannot admit,</hi> Let. p. 51.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, and dehorting, though not ſimply as to the terms, yet as to the things ſignified by them; for the elicite acts of the will, being the Object of Predetermination, [conteſted for], we may at firſt ſight perceive it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compell'd; and ſo as to the event, infers but a <hi>neceſſity of infallibility,</hi> as to the ſinners doing what he is dehorted from, (which alſo Preſcience does).</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> goes on, <hi>Let it be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed only, that the bleſſed God hath belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his nature univerſal Preſcience, we will ſurely, upon that ſuppoſition, acknowledg it to belong to him as a perfection. And were it reaſonable to affirm that by a perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he is diſabled for Government? or wer
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:101372:59"/>it a good conſequence, he foreknows all things, he is therefore unfit to govern the world?</hi> Let. p. 54.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> And why may not we as well ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue thus, Let it be but ſuppoſed only, that univerſal Predetermination belongs to Gods nature, we will upon that ſuppoſition ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it a perfection. And were it reaſonable to affirm, that by a perfection [that he not only conſerves the powers of his creatures, but reduces them to act] he is diſabled for government; or were it a good conſequence, He is the firſt cauſe, [not only of all beings], but of all actions as ſuch, therefore he is unfit to govern the world? And I will add; nay ſurely, but the more fit in the preſent ſtate of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, [not to intermeddle now with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels], becauſe all the actions of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either in whole or in part ſinful, he would have nothing to govern, if he had not the government of all their actions; and govern them he could not, nor limit them, nor turn them to good, if he did not Predetermine them, (as hath been, I truſt, clearly evinced).</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Would the ſuppoſition of ſuch foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in God make that ceaſe to be mans duty, which had otherwiſe been ſo?</hi> Let. p. 54. <hi>for what influence can foreknowledg have to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or affect any way, either the nature of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:101372:59"/>the thing foreknown, or the Temper of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhall do it, any more than the preſent knowledg of the ſame thing now in doing?</hi> p. 55.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> And can Predetermination make that ceaſe to be mans duty, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had been ſo? ſeeing that it alters not the nature of the thing: [the will of man], nor the Temper of the perſon [Predetermin'd]; but as it finds the will free, ſo it leaves it; and as it finds the perſon diſpoſed by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual inclinations, ſo works upon him; which is confirmed, by that grave obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his, which we embrace as our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial friend, and confederate. <hi>It were very unreaſonable to imagine, that God cannot in any caſe, extraordinarily overſway the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and determine the will of ſuch a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as over whom Gods general courſe of Government is by moral inſtruments,</hi> [viz. <hi>Man], in a way agreeable enough to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Let.</hi> p. 141. Only we extend it further, That ſuppoſing, (what hath been before proved), that Predetermination includes a Perfection, God can <hi>in all caſes</hi> determine the will, without forcing it to actions to which it hath a renitency; for that were to alter the nature of the will, and the temper of the perſon whoſe will it is. And I add, what influence can <hi>fore-determining</hi> have to alter the nature of the thing, or
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:101372:60"/>perſon fore-determined, more than <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate concurrence</hi> to the ſame action, of the ſame perſon, now in doing?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>But if what was otherwiſe mans duty, be ſtill his duty, what can make it unfit, that it be made known and declared to him to be ſo? and how is that otherwiſe to be done, than by theſe diſputed means? yea, (for this is the caſe), what can make it leſs fit, than that God ſhould quit the right of his Government to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted creatures, upon no other reaſon, than only that he foreſees they have a mind to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade it?</hi> Let. p. 56.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> All this Argumentation fits our Predetermination as well as Preſcience, (wherein Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> and we agree): what can make it unfit that God ſhould acquaint man with his duty, by proper means, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Predetermination ſuppoſes ſuch a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg (as Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> ſuppoſes, antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Gods decree) of the creatures ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mind to invade Gods right of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, if put under ſuch and ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; or rather, (becauſe we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not any foreknowledg, but of <hi>Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium, things poſſible,</hi> not <hi>Futurorum, of things future,</hi> antecedent to Gods decree) ſeeing Gods determination of the Creatures will to invade his right, without which he could not will ſo to do, leaves the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will as truly free from Co-action, as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101372:60"/>if it exerted all its elicite acts, only by a power derived from God, and preſerved apt and habile for action.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>But it may now be ſaid, All this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning,</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Howe), tends but to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this aſſertion; that notwithſtanding God did foreknow mans ſin, it is however neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary he forewarn him of it: but it anſwers not the objected difficulty,</hi> (viz.) <hi>How rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably any ſuch means are uſed for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attainable end: as it manifeſts the end, mans obedience cannot be attained, when it is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known he will not obey,</hi> Let. p. 57.</p>
               <p>To this difficulty Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> anſwers, <hi>That there is this noble and important end, which Gods Edicts aim at,</hi> (viz.) <hi>the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Decorum of his Government it ſelf. And that he may be found in every thing to have done as became him, and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of himſelf. And what could be more ſo, than to teſtifie his averſion to whatſoever is unholy, his love of righteouſneſs, and compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency to be imitated herein, together with his propenſion to make them happy, who do imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him,</hi> p. 61. [I take here but the ſum of Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s words, becauſe they contain nothing controverſal].</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Whether this Diſcourſe affords us any new conſideration or no, yet we can claim the benefit of it in the fulleſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it to Preſcience, as to Predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation alſo.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:101372:61"/>
               <p n="2">2. As to <hi>Gods ſincerity, the difficulty may ſtill urge, how it can ſtand with ſincerity; whereas that end alſo which fails,</hi> [viz. <hi>mans obedient compliance with Gods Declarations of his will,</hi> p. 60.] <hi>ſeems to have been moſt directly intended,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 65. To which Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> anſwers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the publick Declarations of the Divine will do attain that very end in great part, and as to many, and are the ſucceſsful means of obtaining it,</hi> p. 66.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> And ſo they do upon our Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, who acknowledg God firſt infuſes gracious habits into ſome, and then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the powers in which theſe habits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, to congenerous actions; which yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not the uſe of Gods Edicts, as means of educing thoſe actions: <hi>which becauſe they are vital and free paſſing from the Will, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a compariſon made in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding between the Goodneſs of the Objects propoſed to it, do require a moral cauſe, whereby the Agent may both underſtand the Object, and by Arguments be induced to imbrace it,</hi> (as the Learned <hi>Parker</hi> obſerves, <hi>Theſ. de Trad. Pecc. ad vitam Th.</hi> 27.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Nor was it neceſſary that thoſe who would obey ſhould be ſever'd from the reſt, and be dealt withal apart, &amp;c.</hi> p. 67.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> This we alſo aſſent heartily unto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Nor was it neceſſary, that effectual
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101372:61"/>care ſhould be taken that they ſhould actually reach all, and be applied to every individual perſon,</hi> p. 67.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Here is a ſtrange loſs we are put to for an Antecedent to the Relative, <hi>They.</hi> The only one that I can meet with is, <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick declarations of the Divine will touching mans duty,</hi> p. 66. and <hi>Divine Edicts,</hi> p. 67. and I cannot fathom the reaſon of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of their neceſſity to their two ends by himſelf aſſigned, <hi>Mans Obedience, and the Decorum of the Divine Government;</hi> at leaſt if he means by them the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> (as I gather from his after-diſcourſe.) If he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends by his Relative <hi>They, determinative influences to holy actions, to which the nature of man is now viciouſly inclined,</hi> (as he elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſpeaks, <hi>Poſt. p.</hi> 40, <hi>&amp;</hi> 35, compar'd) I cannot find that <hi>Antecedent</hi> in his whole Diſcourſe foregoing: yet the following paſſages might give a ſuſpicious perſon ſome ground to pitch upon this latter for Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s meaning. <hi>And thus [by meſſengers running from Nation to Nation, ſome to communicate, others to inquire after the tydings of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel] how eaſily, and even naturally would the Goſpel ſoon have ſpread it ſelf through the world?</hi> Let. p. 69. I confeſs that term <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> will not down with me: for I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſeen cauſe to own Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi>'s weighty ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>in his Souls Conflict, That though
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:101372:62"/>there are ſeeds of the Law, yet there are none of the Goſpel in man by nature.</hi> But upon ſecond thoughts to do Mr. <hi>H.</hi> all the right I can, out of love to his perſon, and the truth, I find, That the <hi>They</hi> refers to <hi>the Divine Edicts of the Goſpel, which he ſuppoſes not needful to be immediately by the Miniſtry; but the tranſmiſſion of it from thoſe that have heard it publiſhed by them, may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to others.</hi> But to what end he expati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates upon this I do not know; though I do what ill uſe Mr. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> in his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans debt and dowry,</hi> makes of this very notion. <hi>Sed meliora ſpero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Nor was it incongruous that God ſhould provide by ſome extraordinary means that his gracious tenders might not finally be reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by all.</hi> Let. p. 74.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Yet it ſeems not of ſuch abſolute neceſſity (as I always conceived it to be) <hi>if by the diſpenſations of God towards the whole community of mankind,</hi> [whereof he reckons inſtances, and addes] <hi>they might underſtand God to have favourable propenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards them, and that though they have offended him, he is not their implacable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and might by his goodneſs be led to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> Let. p. 75, 77, compar'd. For thus Mr. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> argues againſt the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of the Goſpel ſtrictly taken. And in Phraſes ſo near, that my fancy is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:101372:62"/>ready to abuſe me with a miſtake, that not <hi>J. H.</hi> but <hi>J. G.</hi> is now diſcourſing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, <hi>The long-ſuffering of God and goodneſs of God are ſaid to lead men to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, becauſe they teſtifie according to a rational and clear interpretation, a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and readineſs in God to receive all ſuch into grace and favour with himſelf, who ſhall unfeignedly repent of their ſins.</hi> So Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> Pagans debt and dowry, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. And he adds, <hi>There is no other conſideration but this, (at leaſt none without this) in reſpect whereof the patience and bountifulneſs of God can be ſaid to lead,</hi> i.e. <hi>to perſwade or invite to repentance. There is no motive or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, whereof ſinners are capable unto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without hope of pardon upon repentance.</hi> Id. Ib. <hi>And concludes you ſee it clear from the Scripture, that even Heathen men, and thoſe that want the Hiſtory of the Goſpel have yet a ſufficiency of means whereby to believe, and ſo to prevent the wrath and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is to come.</hi> Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Ib. p. 14. I muſt profeſs I am none of Mr. <hi>J. G</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, who ever be; nor was Mr. <hi>Obadiah Howe,</hi> a moſt worthy perſon, and kinſman of our Learned Antagoniſt, who hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly and largely confuted him, in a Tract intituled ſignificantly, <hi>The Pagan Preacher ſilenced,</hi> out of whom I ſhall tranſcribe his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>J. G</hi>'s Explication of <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:101372:63"/>2.4. of Heathens. <hi>This ſecond Chapter relates to the</hi> Jews, <hi>whom he reprehends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by their Law they would condemn the Gentiles as ſinners, when they committed the ſame things. But that the patience [and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God] afforded to the</hi> Jews <hi>was without the word, I think</hi> Mr. G. <hi>will not affirm, which is the cauſe why the Apoſtle concludes the</hi> Jews <hi>under a great inexcuſability, becauſe the miniſtry of the word ſuperadded to the light of nature, became not efficacious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from ſin; and from this very Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument he argues againſt the Jews,</hi> v. 17, 18. <hi>ſtill ſuppoſing that theſe perſons enjoying the patience of God,</hi> v. 4. <hi>had the letter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</hi> So far Mr. <hi>Ob. Howe,</hi> p. 52.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>As to thoſe with whom Gods Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ſucceed not well, it is to be conſidered, that he doth not apply himſelf to every (or to any perſon) immediately, and ſeverally, after ſome ſuch tenour of ſpeech as this; I know thee to be a profligate, hopeleſs wretch, and that thou wilt finally diſregard whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſay to thee, and conſequently periſh, and become miſerable. But however (though I foreſee moſt certainly thou wilt not, yet I entreat thee to hear and obey, and live.</hi> Let. p. 79. And afterwards, <hi>What is endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured for the reducement of ſuch—is by ſubſtituted Miniſters, that know no more of the event than they do themſelves,</hi> p. 81.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:101372:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Nor doth God apply himſelf to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in ſuch a tenour of ſpeech with refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Predetermination of thoſe natural actions; which becauſe ſuch need a cauſe acting efficiently for the production of them: though he knows (without ſpecial grace which to them he affords not) a moral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquity will adhere to them. And it is as true, that what God does for the reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them is by Miniſters, who know as little who are Predetermined to good, and who to ſinful actions, as the Saints or Sinners ſo Predetermined.</p>
               <p>Having diſcourſed thus more laxely, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> proceeds to a more ſtrict diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What may be alledged out of Gods word in reference to them that finally periſh in their wickedneſs, which can be thought not conſiſtent with ſincerity to have inſerted, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſuppoſed foreſight of ſo diſmal an iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue?</hi> Let. p. 82. <hi>And he inſtances in Gods profeſſing to will the ſalvation of all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4, <hi>Not to deſire the death of him that dieth,</hi> Ezek. 18.32; <hi>Yea, and profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf grieved that any periſh,</hi> Pſalm 81.12, 13. Ib.</p>
               <p>In anſwer to which Scripture in general (beſides many things ſaid well): he ſays, <hi>That which Gods declarations do amount un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That if they neglect to attend to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:101372:64"/>theſe external diſcoveries of the word,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they are not to expect he ſhould over-power them by a ſtrong hand, and ſave them againſt the continual diſinclination of their own wills.</hi> p. 89, 90.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> I am not able to make ſenſe of the laſt words: For I underſtand not what over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming by a ſtrong hand (in a ſinners caſe) God can make uſe of, that leaves the will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diſinclination to ſalvation; And they ſeem to be repugnant to another Clauſe referring to the ſame perſons: <hi>that they cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe themſelves ſuch power ſhall be uſed with them, as ſhall finally overcome their averſe diſaffected hearts.</hi> p. 90.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> adds, <hi>Whatſover extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Acts, God may do upon ſome to make them willing.</hi> p. 90.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> I am not well ſatisfied (becauſe I am not ignorant of the <hi>Arminians</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion about <hi>Pauls</hi> Converſion) that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> calls thoſe Acts by which God makes ſome men willing, <hi>extraordinary:</hi> for though they are <hi>ſupernatural,</hi> yet they are <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> to all that are willing. It ſeems to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that ſome are made willing by <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> acts, and others by <hi>extraordinary:</hi> And ſo it is an ill-ſounding word.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> at laſt gives us the import of the above-cited Scripture, That they <hi>really ſignifie the obedience and bleſſedneſs
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:101372:64"/>of thoſe his Creatures that are capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to be more pleaſing and agreeable to his nature and will, than that they ſhould diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and periſh, which is the utmoſt can be meant [particularly] by thoſe words, God will have all men to be ſaved and to come to the knowledg of the truth.</hi> p. 93, 94.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> As theſe words ſound they do not gratify my ear: For I cannot underſtand, that the Connexion of Diſobedience and Deſtruction, ſhould not be as agreeable to Gods Will and Nature, as the Connexion of Obedience and Salvation. I take the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, <hi>We</hi> [Apoſtles] <hi>are unto God a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh:</hi> that God takes pleaſure in the periſhing of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, as well as in the ſaving of believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet <hi>in ſano ſenſu,</hi> I admit them as the moſt learned and pious <hi>Davenant, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Biſhop of Salisbury,</hi> explains the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>When God commandeth any thing which is good, he unfeignedly liketh and loveth ſuch actions, and can do no other; his own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral goodneſs, and holineſs terminating,</hi> Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem divinae complacentiae [i. e. <hi>the will of divine Complacence] unto all holy actions by whomſoever performed,</hi> Animadv. <hi>on</hi> Hoard, p. 350. <hi>And Gods meaning when he offereth any grace to men, is, that they ſhould perform ſuch actions whereunto ſuch
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:101372:65"/>grace conduceth; and his meaning when he promiſeth glory to any man if he believeth and perſeveres, is truly to perform it if he do ſo.</hi> Id. pag. 353. And not to ſever the learned Biſhops ſentiments: To Mr. <hi>Hoards</hi> notion [the ſame with Mr. <hi>Howes],</hi> that <hi>mercy is more natural and pleaſing to God than Vindicative Juſtice, which is his ſtrange work; He doth not willingly afflict,</hi> &amp;c. [for which are quoted, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.33]. The Biſhop replyes, <hi>That is ſaid to be natural and pleaſing to God, which comes originally from himſelf, and is not an act depending upon the miſdeſerts of the Creature.</hi> p. 206. <hi>As for Vindicative Juſtice it may be called a ſtrange work, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is</hi> opus occaſionatum [i. e. <hi>a work occaſioned] by mans tranſgreſſion.</hi> p. 287.</p>
               <p>And once more to cite this eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; <hi>The abſolute liberty and ſupreme do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, which God hath in the preparing, or not preparing of effectual grace, wherein the abſolute decrees of Election and non-Election do ſhew themſelves, is a thing as natural and pleaſing to God as his mercy.</hi> p. 287.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> aſſerts, <hi>That God doth ſo far really will the ſalvation of all, as not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the doing that which may effect it, if they be not neglectful of themſelves, but not ſo as to effect it by that extraordinary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertion of power, which he thinks fit to employ upon ſome others.</hi> Let. p. 105.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:101372:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This muſt be mixed with a grain of ſalt: If this omiſſion of Gods refer only to the uſe of means for effecting mens ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, we grant, that <hi>in genere medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> God is not wanting to them that live under the Goſpel-diſpenſations. And in this ſenſe God repreſenting himſelf under the ſimilitude of an Husbandman, truly ſays of <hi>Iſrael, What could have been done more to my Vineyard, that I have not done in it? Iſa.</hi> 5.4. But if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> intends (as the words ſeem to ſound) that ſalvation may be obtained by the uſe of means, without that exertion of power (which he calls <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi>) whereby that end is obtained in ſome, I cannot take ſuch an aſſertion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his bare word. I have been taught from my Childhood (and ſee no cauſe to ſuſpect the credulity of that age abuſed to draw me into a misbelief) that ſuch an exertion of power, as whereby God raiſed Chriſt from the dead, is univerſally neceſſary to make the means of ſalvation effectual to their end.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> profeſſes his diſlike of the common diſtinction of <hi>Voluntas beneplaciti &amp; ſigni, in this preſent caſe</hi> [viz. <hi>to explain how God wills the ſalvation of all, and yet only of ſome] under which ſuch as coyned, and thoſe that have much uſed it, have only rather I doubt not, conceal'd a good meaning
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:101372:66"/>than expreſſed by it a bad one.</hi> p. 106.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> And whoever coined it (which I take it was <hi>Hugo de S. Victore</hi>) few of our Divines but have uſed it, that have dealt in any Controverſie which gave an occaſion for it. And why ſhould Mr. <hi>H.</hi> charge them with a concealment of a good meaning, which they have ſo often diſcovered? If Mr. <hi>H.</hi> only diſlkes the terms, I ſhould not contend with him, for I can give him their ſenſe in others from the learned <hi>Davenant; The will of God termed</hi> voluntas ſimplicis complacentiae, <hi>i. e. the will of ſimple compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency [which is the ſame with</hi> vol. ſigni] <hi>and that which is termed</hi> voluntas abſoluta <hi>or</hi> eſſicax <hi>i. e. an abſolute or efficacious will [which is the ſame with</hi> vol. beneplaciti] <hi>may well ſtand together. God wills that all men believe and be ſaved with the will of compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; God wills and decrees to permit that ſome continue in unbelief, and be not ſaved but periſh, with the Abſolute will. The former will in effect is but a conditional will; As if the Apoſtle had ſaid, God will have all men to be ſaved, if all men ſhall believe in Chriſt; and to believe in Chriſt is an act ſo well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſo agreeable unto Gods will, that whereſoever it is found it ſhall be rewarded. But notwithſtanding the extent of this will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, there is in God an abſolute will of permitting ſome to continue in their unbelief,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:101372:66"/>and ſo periſh,</hi> Dav. ag. Hoard, p. 220.</p>
               <p>But it muſt be obſerved, that whereas the moſt learned Biſhop ſeems to attribute a <hi>Conditional will to God</hi> above; he afterwards explains himſelf, <hi>Meer or purely conditional Decrees</hi> agree not with the perfection of the Divine Nature. The ſpeeches therefore ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of Scripture <hi>[He that believes ſhall be ſaved, &amp;c.]</hi> do not imply a Conditional Will in God ſuſpended for any moment of time, and then <hi>poſt purificatam conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> i. e. after the Condition performed] becoming an abſolute and effectual will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But theſe conditional Decrees are grounded on ſome abſolute revealed Decree of God, to the Performance whereof he hath tied himſelf. For example, it is an abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Divine Will publiſhed in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>that whoſoever believeth,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall be ſaved. From hence is derived that mixt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Decree; If <hi>Cain, Judas,</hi> or any other believe, they ſhall be ſaved. Now ſuch mixt conditional Decrees carry no contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the abſolute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who ſeeth not theſe Propoſitions may well ſtand together? I will that if <hi>Judas</hi> repent and believe, he ſhall have remiſſion and ſalvation. I will not to give to <hi>Judas</hi> the gift of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, of faith and of eternal life, <hi>Id.</hi> p. 225, 226, 227. I have ſaid enough to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate M. <hi>H</hi>'s exagitation of the terms <hi>Vol.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:101372:67"/>ſigni &amp; beneplaciti,</hi> which are not worth the trouble of tranſcribing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But M. <hi>H.</hi> adds, <hi>And of theſe faults the application of the diſtinction of Gods ſecret and revealed Will unto this caſe, though it be uſeful in many, is as guilty.</hi> Let. p. 108.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. As to this I ſay (as the aforeſaid Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> of M. <hi>Hoard);</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhould firſt have rightly ſet it down, and then have tried his ſtrength in confuting it, and I ſhall add his explication of it: We ſay that there is in God a true will revealed in the Goſpel of ſaving all men that ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and a true will liking, embracing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding faith, holineſs, perſeverance in all men whomſoever without diſtinction of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: And this is the Will call'd <hi>Voluntas ſimplicis complacentiae</hi> [or <hi>ſigni</hi>] which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther decreeth nor determineth any thing infallibly concerning the being or not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch good acts in this or that ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon. This Will we know, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we call it his <hi>revealed will.</hi> There is alſo in God a ſecret will of bringing ſome men to faith, perſeverance, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, and of not bringing others to any of theſe: this Will we know not, and therefore we call it, the <hi>ſecret Will, Dav. ag. Hoard,</hi> p. 221: only 'tis to be noted, that when the Reverend Biſhop ſays, <hi>This ſecret will of God we know not;</hi> it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:101372:67"/>with reference to the particular perſons whom God intends to work faith, &amp;c. in; for we know in general, that there are ſome perſons whom God will be thus good unto. I add this to prevent a Cavil, which may ſeem very acute to them that uſe it: If God's will of good pleaſure [or abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute will] be ſecret, how come we to know it? or if it be revealed, how is it ſecret? <hi>And then the members of the diſtinction are confounded</hi> (as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> objects, p. 107.) who ſhould have done well to have told us, in what caſes it is uſeful (though not in the preſent caſe). For I dare offer my ſelf to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the uſe of it in any caſe, upon the ſame grounds that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can the uſe of it in this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 2. And yet when Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath ſo ſolemnly declared his diſlike of our diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, he owns it himſelf, but in other words, which are the explication of our terms: <hi>And whereas it may be thought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hence, that hereby we aſcribe to God a liableneſs to fruſtration and diſappointment, that is without pretence: The reſolve of the Divine will in this matter</hi> [viz. <hi>the holineſs and ſalvation of all men</hi>] <hi>being not concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the event what man ſhall do, but concerning his duty what he ſhould, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the connexion between his duty and his happineſs,</hi> Let. p. 112.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:101372:68"/>
               <p>Now to leave Mr. <hi>H.</hi> inexcuſable for the impertinency of his exception againſt our Diſtinction; let us ſee how Dr <hi>Twiſſe (a man that much uſed this diſtinction,</hi> and therefore blamed by Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) explains it. There is no contradiction, ſays he, between theſe two wills Divine: For <hi>Voluntas ſigni</hi> is impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called a Will, for it ſignifies only <hi>mans duty, or what he ſhould do,</hi> as what will be pleaſing to God if it be done. But <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas beneplaciti</hi> is properly and ſimply a will, (<hi>viz.</hi> whereby is decreed whatſoever ſhall come to paſs, by Gods either efficiency, or permiſſion) <hi>Twiſſe Vind. Gr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 1. §. 12. <hi>p.</hi> 140. It is evident to any intelligent Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator, that M <hi>H</hi>'s and Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi>'s ſenſe is the ſame, and ſo Mr <hi>H.</hi> hath blamed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in blaming <hi>Twiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>And if it ſhould be inſiſted, that in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting God to will what by his Laws he hath made become mans duty, even where it is not done, we ſhall herein aſcribe to him, at leaſt an ineffectual and imperfect will, as that which doth not bring to paſs the thing willed: It is anſwer'd, that Imperfection were with no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence imputable to the Divine will, meerly for not effecting every thing whereto it may have a real propenſion,</hi> Let. p. 115, 116.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> We had need tread warily here, for our way is ſtrewed with Daggers, I mean, with terms repugnant to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:101372:68"/>
               <p n="1">1. If God be underſtood but to <hi>will mans duty, not the event</hi> [his obedience to it] there's no colour for the Objection, that the will of God is ineffectual; for it is effectual (when declared) to make mans duty what it pleaſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If by <hi>willing mans duty,</hi> he means <hi>the event</hi> [the performance of it], then is there an Objection indeed, but without ſolution, and not capable of any.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Take it how you will, there's no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Objection. For this is, <hi>That Gods will is ineffectual if that come not to paſs which is willed:</hi> and that is, That <hi>God hath no will at all of that which comes not to paſs</hi> [which yet the Objection ſuppoſes] for what elſe is the meaning of a real <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion,</hi> which differs as much from willing as an habit from an act, or as the power of ſeeing when my eyes are ſhut, from my actual ſeeing when they are open?</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Nor could any courſe have been taken that was fit in himſelf, and more agreeable to ſincerity</hi> [viz. <hi>than counſels, and exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whatſoever means God uſes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent mens ſins]. There are only two ways to be thought on beſides, either that God ſhould wholly have forborn to make overtures to man in common, or that he ſhould efficaciouſly have overpowr'd all into a compliance with them. And there is little doubt, but upon ſober con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:101372:69"/>both of theſe will be judged altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit,</hi> Let. p. 121.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> As to the <hi>former</hi> of theſe two ways, I have nothing to oppoſe; As to the <hi>Latter,</hi> there is a great deal of doubt; and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> implies ſo much when he ſays, <hi>it is loſs obvious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> proceeds to ſhew the unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods efficacious overpowring all men into a compliance with his Overtures to them, becauſe of two congruities in the courſe taken for the Government of the World.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That it be ſteady and uniform; not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by frequent, extraordinary and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomalous actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That he uſe a royal Liberty, of ſtepping out of his uſual courſe ſometimes, as he ſees meet,</hi> p. 131, 132; and adds, <hi>If we apply them to the affairs of Grace, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing correſpondent. That ordinarily</hi> [grace] <hi>be ſought and expected, in the uſe of ordinary means. And that ſometimes its Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhew it ſelf in preventive exertions; and in working ſo Heroically, as none have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hand, in the neglect of its ordinary me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, any reaſon to expect,</hi> p. 138.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. This Anſwer is not fitted to the Queſtion. The Queſtion is, <hi>Whether it be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for God efficaciouſly to overpower all men into a compliance with the overtures he makes
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:101372:69"/>to them in common?</hi> The Anſwer is, <hi>It is not fit for God to overpower m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, without making any overtures to them at all:</hi> or to alter the terms and keep the ſenſe, the Queſtion is, <hi>Whether it be fitting, that God ſhould give all men ſpecial grace, in the uſe of means?</hi> And the Anſwer is, It is not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that God ſhould give all men ſpecial grace, without the uſe of means. An admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable incogitancy in a man of parts. If the Queſtion had been about the fitneſs of Gods converting all men (whom he thinks meet to convert) as he did <hi>Saul,</hi> by a voice from Heaven; the Anſwer had been a-kin to the Queſtion: (though even <hi>Saul</hi> was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted without means, but without ordinary means).</p>
               <p n="2">2. I am at a loſs for a Reaſon, why it ſhould be unfit for God efficaciouſly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpower all men into a compliance with the means (ſuppoſing what I hope Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will not deny, I am ſure will never be able to diſprove; that no man will ever comply with the means, that is not overpowr'd thereunto) unleſs it be this, that it is unfit for God to beſtow grace, and ſalvation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men (which would be a very hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 2. As to his ſecond <hi>Theſis,</hi> if it be (as 'tis pretended) an Anſwer to the Queſtion propoſed. I Anſwer, That though
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:101372:70"/>it be fitting enough for God to <hi>uſe a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al liberty</hi> in giving grace to ſome, and not to others; yet I underſtand not that the ſuſpenſion of his Liberty, and binding up himſelf to give grace to all, had been any way unfit. We poor Mortals, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, are very unfit to judg what is fit or unfit for God to do. We may reſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that God does nothing but what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him: but we ſhall intermeddle in things too high for us, if we paſs ſentence, that for God to do otherwiſe in many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances than he hath done, would unbecome him. God hath permitted the whole race of mankind to turn Rebels to his Soveraign Majeſty, and but ſome part of the Angelical nature. This became him to do, becauſe he hath done it. But ſuppoſe he had preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Rebellion of all his rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; or mans, and not the Angels; or the Angels, and not mans; or permitted the Rebellion of all the Angels, (as he hath of all mankind); or reſtored the Angels, and left man in his own ruins: would Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> adventure to ſay, that <hi>upon ſober conſideration any of theſe ways would have been judged altogether unfit for God to have taken?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Mr. <hi>How</hi> proceeds, and acquaints us, <hi>that it were incongruous that a whole order of Intelligent creatures ſhould be moved only by
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:101372:70"/>inward impulſes: — And that the faculties, whereby men are capable of moral Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould be rendered to this purpoſe</hi> [viz. the Improvement of means] <hi>uſeleſs and vain. And that they ſhould be tempted to expect to be conſtantly managed as meer Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines, that know not their own uſe,</hi> Let. pag. 142, 143.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Either this Harangue is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, or it borders as near upon <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm</hi> as <hi>Scotland</hi> does upon <hi>England.</hi> If Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s meaning be, that it is incongruous for God to overpower men, that <hi>neglect the means</hi> [as his words <hi>p.</hi> 142, imply] where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Queſtion he undertook to Anſwer is, <hi>Whether it be congruous for God to overpower all</hi> (as he does ſome) <hi>that uſe the means,</hi> then his Diſcourſe is beſides the buſineſs; or if he would inſinuate, that <hi>the courſe which God takes with ſome</hi> [though not with all] <hi>in overpowring them, is to manage them as Machines, and render their natural facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vain and uſeleſs;</hi> This is <hi>Arminius</hi>'s Charge upon the Proteſtant Doctrines of the <hi>irreſiſtible operation of ſpecial grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To draw now to a cloſe, after too long a Diſcourſe, (that I may not tire my Reader) I ſhall only requeſt him, that he would duly conſider, that of Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Principles there are theſe deſperate conſequences, (which I have ſo much charity as to believe he does
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:101372:71"/>not ſee, and (ſo) nor own,) That God is juſtled out of his proper place; I mean, of being the firſt cauſe of all the Creatures actions, and the Creature put in his ſtead, as being repreſented able to uſe its powers, as it pleaſes. That one great Perfection of the Divine Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Foreknowledg of future Contingencies, is ſeparated from it, by denying the only true ground of ſuch Foreknowledg, the Divine Decrees. And hence, the Providence of God in governing the actions of his Creatures is left in great danger of falling, becauſe a Superſtructure raiſed without a foundation. For how can God govern thoſe actions which depend not immediately upon him in their production; nor are foreknown in his <hi>Eternal Decree,</hi> wherein lies the model of all he intends to exerciſe his Government upon, <hi>in time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſum, his Doctrine opens a wide door for Atheiſm, and deſerves as ſharp a cenſure as one gave of <hi>Epicurus</hi>'s denial of Providence, <hi>Verbis Deum poſuit, re ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tulit;</hi> i.e. <hi>He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged God in words, but denied him in deed.</hi> For as all Arguments proving any of the <hi>Divine Attributes,</hi> do prove a <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>thoſe terms are eſſentially convertible:</hi> ſo thoſe Arguments which deny any <hi>Divine Attributes,</hi> do alſo deny a <hi>God</hi> upon the ſame ground.</p>
               <p>I ſhall give the Reader no further
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:101372:71"/>trouble but what (if he be conſcientious) he will willingly give himſelf of examining what he hath read, and judging according to the evidence of <hi>Truth;</hi> for which in this momentous Controverſie, and not for <hi>victory</hi> I have entred into this publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with my ancient and learned Friend, Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> which I take to be ſufficiently warranted by that paſſage of holy Writ: <hi>But when Peter was come to Antioch I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed,</hi> Gal. 2.11. Whence it may be duly collected, that the reverence or eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of any mans perſon ought not to hinder a publick reproof, when he is guilty of a publick ſcandal.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EPiſt.</hi> P. 4. l. 9. r. efforts. l. 14. r. an. p. 6. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. you. p. 7. l. 21. r. lapt. l. 29. r. efforts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Book,</hi> p. 3. l. 30. r. in theſe terms. p. 4. blot out the three firſt lines, and an half. p. 13. l. 1. r. <hi>materiale.</hi> p. 20. l. 3. after impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded r. 2ly. p. 22. l. 3. for 3. r. 2. p. 58. l. 26. for word r. work. p. 73. l. 28. after is r. true. p. 87. l. 26. r. reverend.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
